<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Return>
  <ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCnt="0">
    <ReturnTs>2019-02-15T15:47:52-06:00</ReturnTs>
    <TaxPeriodEndDt>2018-04-30</TaxPeriodEndDt>
    <PreparerFirmGrp>
      <PreparerFirmEIN>943194056</PreparerFirmEIN>
      <PreparerFirmName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>THE HENRY LEVY GROUP</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </PreparerFirmName>
      <PreparerUSAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>5940 COLLEGE AVE STE F</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>OAKLAND</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>CA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>946181385</ZIPCd>
      </PreparerUSAddress>
    </PreparerFirmGrp>
    <ReturnTypeCd>990EZ</ReturnTypeCd>
    <TaxPeriodBeginDt>2017-05-01</TaxPeriodBeginDt>
    <Filer>
      <EIN>680475089</EIN>
      <BusinessName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>WIXARIKA RESEARCH CENTER</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </BusinessName>
      <BusinessNameControlTxt>WIXA</BusinessNameControlTxt>
      <PhoneNum>5104201116</PhoneNum>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>863 LEO WAY</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>OAKLAND</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>CA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>946111964</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
    </Filer>
    <BusinessOfficerGrp>
      <PersonNm>YVONNE NEGRIN</PersonNm>
      <PersonTitleTxt>EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR</PersonTitleTxt>
      <PhoneNum>5104201445</PhoneNum>
      <SignatureDt>2019-02-11</SignatureDt>
    </BusinessOfficerGrp>
    <PreparerPersonGrp>
      <PreparerPersonNm>BETH ATTEBERY</PreparerPersonNm>
      <PTIN>P01466121</PTIN>
      <PhoneNum>5106521000</PhoneNum>
      <PreparationDt>2019-02-14</PreparationDt>
    </PreparerPersonGrp>
    <FilingSecurityInformation>
      <IPAddress>
        <IPv4AddressTxt>64.88.174.3</IPv4AddressTxt>
      </IPAddress>
      <IPDt>2019-02-15</IPDt>
      <IPTm>15:47:52</IPTm>
      <IPTimezoneCd>CS</IPTimezoneCd>
      <FilingLicenseTypeCd>P</FilingLicenseTypeCd>
      <AtSubmissionCreationDeviceId>B0C469008A350E6022469A353BFE1123375C9446</AtSubmissionCreationDeviceId>
      <AtSubmissionFilingDeviceId>9B6C7823324A2BC9EFE6DE07C9373DAA621D5869</AtSubmissionFilingDeviceId>
    </FilingSecurityInformation>
    <TaxYr>2017</TaxYr>
    <BuildTS>2019-02-21 02:37:17Z</BuildTS>
  </ReturnHeader>
  <ReturnData documentCnt="4">
    <IRS990EZ documentId="RetDoc3" referenceDocumentId="RetDoc4">
      <MethodOfAccountingCashInd>X</MethodOfAccountingCashInd>
      <WebsiteAddressTxt>WWW.WIXARIKA.ORG</WebsiteAddressTxt>
      <Organization501c3Ind referenceDocumentId="RetDoc5">X</Organization501c3Ind>
      <TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>X</TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>
      <GrossReceiptsAmt>59043</GrossReceiptsAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIInd>
      <ContributionsGiftsGrantsEtcAmt>57798</ContributionsGiftsGrantsEtcAmt>
      <SaleOfAssetsGrossAmt>1245</SaleOfAssetsGrossAmt>
      <CostOrOtherBasisExpenseSaleAmt>1245</CostOrOtherBasisExpenseSaleAmt>
      <TotalRevenueAmt>57798</TotalRevenueAmt>
      <SalariesOtherCompEmplBnftAmt>55232</SalariesOtherCompEmplBnftAmt>
      <FeesAndOtherPymtToIndCntrctAmt>2400</FeesAndOtherPymtToIndCntrctAmt>
      <OccupancyRentUtltsAndMaintAmt>7514</OccupancyRentUtltsAndMaintAmt>
      <PrintingPublicationsPostageAmt>119</PrintingPublicationsPostageAmt>
      <OtherExpensesTotalAmt>9761</OtherExpensesTotalAmt>
      <TotalExpensesAmt>75026</TotalExpensesAmt>
      <ExcessOrDeficitForYearAmt>-17228</ExcessOrDeficitForYearAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>49903</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>32675</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIIInd>
      <CashSavingsAndInvestmentsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>26123</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>4837</EOYAmt>
      </CashSavingsAndInvestmentsGrp>
      <OtherAssetsTotalDetail>
        <BOYAmt>23780</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>27838</EOYAmt>
      </OtherAssetsTotalDetail>
      <Form990TotalAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>49903</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>32675</EOYAmt>
      </Form990TotalAssetsGrp>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>49903</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>32675</EOYAmt>
      </NetAssetsOrFundBalancesGrp>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>
      <PrimaryExemptPurposeTxt>ADVOCACY FOR THE HUICHOL INDIANS IN MEXICO, AND PRESERVATION AND PROMOTION OF THE HUICHOL CULTURE AND ARTWORK.</PrimaryExemptPurposeTxt>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER MAINTAINS AN ONLINE WORLD-CLASS ARCHIVE OF WIXRIKA (HUICHOL) INDIGENOUS ART AND CULTURE TO EDUCATE THE PUBLIC ABOUT THIS UNIQUE AND EXTRAORDINARY CULTURE. THROUGH THE FOUNDATION'S WEB SITE, WE RAISE PUBLIC AWARENESS ABOUT THE CHALLENGES THESE INDIGENOUS PEOPLE ARE FACING TODAY DUE TO THEIR RAPIDLY CHANGING ENVIRONMENT. IT IS OUR HOPE THAT THE WEBSITE WILL AMPLIFY THEIR VOICES AND ADD WEIGHT TO THEIR OPINIONS AND CONCERNS. OUR WEBSITE, WHICH IS PUBLISHED IN ENGLISH AND SPANISH, GIVES THE PUBLIC FREE ACCESS TO IMAGES OF AN EXTRAORDINARY COLLECTION OF THEIR TRADITIONAL, SACRED, AND CONTEMPORARY ART AND PUBLISHES NEWS ON RELEVANT CURRENT EVENTS. WE ALSO MAINTAIN A FACEBOOK GROUP CALLED "HUICHOL CULTURAL SURVIVAL" WHICH IS NOW FOLLOWED BY MORE THAN 4,200 PEOPLE, INCLUDING A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. WE POST NEWS ARTICLES ALMOST DAILY, VIDEOS, AND SHORT FILMS OF INTEREST. OUR POSTS ARE OFTEN COMMENTED ON AND SHARED WHICH IN TURN BRINGS NEW PEOPLE TO OUR GROUP. THE WORK OF THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER (WRC) CONSISTS OF PRESERVING, IN DIGITAL FORMAT, PHOTOGRAPHS, DOCUMENTS, TAPE RECORDINGS AND IMAGES OF SACRED, TRADITIONAL, AND CONTEMPORARY ART, COLLECTED AND/OR PHOTOGRAPHED BY JUAN AND YVONNE NEGRIN FROM 1970 TO PRESENT. THE PAPER ARCHIVES BEING DIGITALIZED INCLUDE COPIES OF DOCUMENTS AND NEWS REPORTS PERTAINING TO PAST AND PRESENT LAND DISPUTES, THE EXPLOITATION OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE'S NATURAL RESOURCES, AND COMMUNITY DOCUMENTS AND PETITIONS DRAWN UP AT THEIR GENERAL ASSEMBLIES. HUNDREDS OF COLOR TRANSPARENCIES TAKEN BY JUAN &amp; YVONNE NEGRIN HAVE BEEN SCANNED IN HIGH RESOLUTION FOR PRESERVATION. THESE PHOTOGRAPHS ARE UNIQUE BECAUSE THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES RARELY PERMITTED CAMERAS TO BE USED TO CAPTURE THEIR WAY OF LIFE, THEIR CEREMONIES, OR THEIR SACRED SPOTS BY OUTSIDERS. AN EXCEPTION WAS MADE IN THE CASE OF THE NEGRNS BECAUSE OF THEIR DEDICATED WORK IN DEFENDING THE LAND AND RESOURCES OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND THE NON-PROFIT NATURE OF THE WORK THEY CARRIED OUT OVER SEVERAL DECADES. THIS IS AN ONGOING PROJECT EXPECTED TO TAKE SUBSTANTIAL TIME TO COMPLETE. THE TAPE RECORDINGS CONSIST OF SACRED CHANTS, ORAL HISTORY AS RECOUNTED BY MEMBERS OF THE COUNCIL OF ELDERS, TRADITIONAL MUSIC, COMMUNITY ASSEMBLIES AND INTERVIEWS. THE ORIGINAL RECORDINGS WERE MADE ON MAGNETIC CASSETTES AND THEIR CONVERSION TO DIGITAL FORMAT IS NECESSARY IN ORDER TO PRESERVE THIS IMPORTANT BODY OF WORK. IN AUGUST OF 2017, WE BEGAN TO DESIGN AND BUILD A LONG OVERDUE NEW WEBSITE AND ONLINE ARCHIVE THAT WILL ENABLE US TO PROVIDE ACCESS TO A LARGE BODY OF HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS, MORE ART EXHIBITS, AND A BETTER DESIGNED NEWS SECTION. IT WILL ALSO HAVE AN EFFICIENT SEARCH ENGINE TO AID THE PUBLIC IN FINDING WHAT THEY ARE LOOKING FOR. WE ESTIMATE THIS PROJECT WILL TAKE CLOSE TO A YEAR TO COMPLETE SINCE WE WILL BE DESIGNING EACH SECTION AS WE GO AND DUE TO THE LARGE BODY OF DOCUMENTS AND EXHIBITS TO BE TRANSFERRED FROM OUR OLD WEBSITE, AND THE MANY NEW DOCUMENTS AND NEWS ITEMS TO BE UPLOADED. THIS PROJECT HAS BEEN UNDERTAKEN BY YVONNE NEGRN WITH THE HELP OF OUR WEB MASTERS WES AND COLETTE HEADLEY OF ACTUAL SYSTEMS. WE ARE PLEASED AT THE PROSPECT OF FINALLY HAVING A WEBSITE THAT WILL BE MUCH MORE USER FRIENDLY, IS CAPABLE OF HANDLING A LARGE DATABASE OF DOCUMENTS, AND BETTER SUITS OUR FOUNDATION'S MISSION, THE NEEDS OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE, AND OUR AUDIENCE. IN SEPTEMBER, WE ENJOYED A NEARLY TWO-MONTH VISIT FROM AUKWE GARCA MIJAREZ, A YOUNG WIXRIKA WOMAN AND RECENT GRADUATE OF ITESO (INSTITUTO TECNOLOGICO DE ESTUDIOS SUPERIORES DE OCCIDENTE) THE JESUIT UNIVERSITY IN GUADALAJARA. AUKWE GRADUATED IN DECEMBER 2016 WITH A DEGREE IN COMMUNICATIONS AND IS THE DIRECTOR OF COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE REGIONAL WIXRIKA COUNCIL THAT IS IN CHARGE OF THE DEFENSE OF THEIR PEOPLES' SACRED LOCATIONS. DURING HER STAY SHE WAS ABLE TO LEARN MORE ABOUT THE WORK OUR FOUNDATION HAS BEEN DOING AND WAS ABLE TO VIEW AND STUDY MANY OF THE ARCHIVES COLLECTED BY JUAN NEGRN OVER HIS LIFETIME OF WORK WITH HER PEOPLE. IN PARTICULAR SHE FOCUSED ON ARCHIVES RELATING TO THE INVASION OF WIXRIKA TERRITORY BY THEIR NEIGHBORS, THE EXPLOITATION OF THEIR FORESTS, AND OTHER RELATED POLITICAL ARCHIVES. SHE TOOK THE TIME TO THOROUGHLY READ OVER ONE HUNDRED DOCUMENTS, MANY OF WHICH WERE MULTIPLE PAGES, SCAN THEM FOR FUTURE UPLOAD TO THE NEW WEBSITE, AND SHE ALSO CREATED AN EXCEL SHEET DESCRIBING THEIR CONTENT AND IMPORTANCE. LATER IN HER TRIP, SHE ATTENDED AND PARTICIPATED IN OUR MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS. AT THE MEETING SHE TOLD US THE DOCUMENTS WERE OF GREAT IMPORTANCE TO HER PEOPLE BECAUSE THEY TOLD THE WHOLE STORY OF HOW HER PEOPLE WERE EXPLOITED ONCE THE FIRST ROAD WAS BUILT IN THE EARLY 1970'S GIVING EASIER ACCESS TO THEIR TERRITORY BY OUTSIDE INTERESTS FOR THE FIRST TIME. SHE EMPHASIZED THAT THIS IS AN IMPORTANT STORY FOR HER PEOPLE TO KNOW SINCE THE YOUNGER GENERATION HAD NOT EVEN BEEN BORN YET. THESE DOCUMENTS WILL FORM A PART OF THE HISTORICAL ARCHIVE THAT WILL BE AVAILABLE ONLINE TO THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND TO ALL OTHERS INTERESTED IN LEARNING ABOUT THIS HISTORY. IN OCTOBER WE CO-HOSTED AN EVENT AT THE SAN FRANCISCO DE YOUNG MUSEUM WITH CINE Y MS. THE EVENT BEGAN WITH A SLIDE PRESENTATION HIGHLIGHTING THE TERRITORY, DAILY LIFE, SACRED PILGRIMAGES, AND CEREMONIES OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND WAS FOLLOWED BY A FILM "THE MARRAKAME'S DREAM" WHICH TOLD THE STORY OF A WIXRIKA HEALER AND HIS SON. AFTER THE FILM DIANA NEGRN AND AUKWE GARCA ANSWERED QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE. THE EVENT WAS VERY WELL RECEIVED BY THE PUBLIC AND IT GAVE THEM AN UNDERSTANDING OF THE CHALLENGES THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE FACE AS THEY STRUGGLE FOR THEIR CULTURAL SURVIVAL. IN MID-DECEMBER, MATSIWA, WHO IS A SPIRITUAL LEADER IN HIS COMMUNITY, CAME TO SPEND THE HOLIDAYS WITH US AND TO TELL US ABOUT THE DELIVERY OF PHOTOGRAPHS AND RECORDINGS HE HAD DELIVERED ON OUR BEHALF TO THE PEOPLE IN THE SIERRAS. ALL THE RECIPIENTS WERE THRILLED WE WERE ESPECIALLY HAPPY THAT THE ORAL HISTORY IS NOW IN THE HANDS OF THE FAMILIES OF THE ELDERS, WHICH IS NOW A PROMISE THAT HAS BEEN KEPT. OF COURSE THERE WERE REQUESTS FOR MORE PHOTOGRAPHS SO WE WILL DO SOME MORE PRINTING FOR THE FAMILY MEMBERS WHO WILL BE WAITING. IN LATE FEBRUARY 2018, DIANA NEGRN TRAVELLED TO MEXICO TO PARTICIPATE IN THE CONFERENCE ON THE SACRED PLANTS OF THE AMERICAS THAT WAS HELD IN AJIJIC ON LAKE CHAPALA. OUR FOUNDATION WAS ONE OF THE SPONSORS OF THE EVENT AND DIANA MODERATED A PANEL OF FIVE WIXRIKA PEOPLE ON THE SUBJECT OF THE EXPLOITATION OF THEIR SACRED PLACES AND SPECIFICALLY THE ONGOING THREAT OF MINING IN THE DESERT OF WIRIKUTA. THE PANEL CONSISTED OF A WIXRIKA LAWYER, THE HEAD OF COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE WIXRIKA REGIONAL COUNCIL FOR THE DEFENSE OF THEIR TERRITORIES, A SHAMAN AND SPIRITUAL LEADER, AND TWO OTHERS, A MAN AND A WOMAN, WHO ARE SPOKESPERSONS FOR THE DEFENSE OF THEIR CULTURE. THE ENTIRE CONFERENCE WAS FILMED AND WE HAVE POSTED VIDEOS ON OUR WEBSITE. DURING THIS FISCAL YEAR WE ALSO BEGAN WORK ON TWO FUTURE EXHIBITS. WE WERE CONTACTED BY TELEVISA THROUGH OUR WEBSITE AND ASKED TO PARTICIPATE IN THEIR EXHIBIT MEXICOLOR WHICH WILL OPEN AT THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS IN MEXICO CITY IN LATE MAY OF 2020. WE RECEIVED A VISIT FROM JOHN OLS, WHO IS CURATING THE EXHIBIT, AND HE CHOSE SIX PHOTOGRAPHS TAKEN OF THE WIXRIKA BY JUAN NEGRN. THREE WILL BE ON EXHIBIT AND ALL SIX WILL APPEAR IN THE BOOK BEING PUBLISHED TO ACCOMPANY THE EXHIBIT. THE SECOND EXHIBIT IS BEING CURATED BY OUR DIRECTOR, DIANA NEGRN, AND IS PLANNED TO OPEN AT THE INSTITUTO CULTURAL CABAAS IN GUADALAJARA AT THE END OF JUNE 2019. THIS EXHIBIT WILL BE MUCH MORE EXTENSIVE CONSISTING OF YARN PAINTINGS, TEXTILES, PHOTOGRAPHS, FILM, AND OF COURSE A CATALOGUE. THE EXHIBIT WILL TRAVEL TO OTHER MUSEUMS IN MEXICO AND HOPEFULLY THE TOUR CAN CLOSE AT A MUSEUM IN THE UNITED STATES. THIS SPRING WE WERE ALSO CONTACTED THROUGH OUR WEBSITE BY THE INTERNATIONAL FRIENDSHIP CLUB IN PUERTO VALLARTA. THIS IS A CLUB OF AMERICANS LIVING IN MEXICO WHO ARE INTERESTED IN HELPING WIXRIKA YOUTH WITH EDUCATIONAL EXPENSES. SINCE THEY ARE INCORPORATED IN MEXICO DONATIONS WILL HAVE TO BE GIVEN TO A FOUNDATION REGISTERED IN MEXICO BUT THEY HAVE ASSIGNED US THE TASK OF LOCATING A MEXICAN NON-PROFIT FOUNDATION WE CAN ALL WORK WITH. IT WILL BE UP TO US TO SCREEN STUDENTS, DELIVER THE SCHOLARSHIPS AND TO FOLLOW UP ON EACH STUDENT'S PROGRESS. WE HOPE THAT THE FIRST SCHOLARSHIPS CAN BE DELIVERED TO STUDENTS IN THE FALL OF 2018. FOR THIS FIRST YEAR, SIX SCHOLARSHIPS OF 5,000 PESOS (258 USD) EACH WILL BE GIVEN AND IF ALL WORKS WELL THE INTERNATIONAL FRIENDSHIP CLUB INTENDS TO EXPAND THE PROGRAM. NEEDLESS TO SAY WE ARE VERY HONORED AND EXCITED TO PARTICIPATE IN THE INITIATIVE TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO DESERVING STUDENTS.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>75026</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>75026</TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>YVONNE NEGRIN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>EXECUTIVE DI</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>40.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>48000</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>2998</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>DIANA NEGRIN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>PRESIDENT</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>12.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>MARIA E CRUZ</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>BOARD MEMBER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>1.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>ANTHONY SOMKIN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>TREASURER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>5.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>DAVID TUSSMAN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>BOARD MEMBER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>1.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>STEPHEN ALDRICH</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>BOARD MEMBER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>1.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>VANESSA SEQUEIRA-GARZA</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>SECRETARY</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>4.00</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <ActivitiesNotPreviouslyRptInd>false</ActivitiesNotPreviouslyRptInd>
      <ChgMadeToOrgnzngDocNotRptInd>false</ChgMadeToOrgnzngDocNotRptInd>
      <OrganizationHadUBIInd>false</OrganizationHadUBIInd>
      <SubjectToProxyTaxInd>false</SubjectToProxyTaxInd>
      <OrganizationDissolvedEtcInd>false</OrganizationDissolvedEtcInd>
      <Form1120PolFiledInd>false</Form1120PolFiledInd>
      <MadeLoansToFromOfficersInd>false</MadeLoansToFromOfficersInd>
      <EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>false</EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>false</ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>CA</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <BooksInCareOfDetail>
        <BusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>YVONNE NEGRIN</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </BusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>863 LEO WAY</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>OAKLAND</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>CA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>946111964</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <PhoneNum>5104201116</PhoneNum>
      </BooksInCareOfDetail>
      <ForeignFinancialAccountInd>false</ForeignFinancialAccountInd>
      <ForeignOfficeInd>false</ForeignOfficeInd>
      <DonorAdvisedFndsInd>false</DonorAdvisedFndsInd>
      <OperateHospitalInd>false</OperateHospitalInd>
      <TanningServicesProvidedInd>false</TanningServicesProvidedInd>
      <RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>false</RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>
      <TransactionWithControlEntInd>false</TransactionWithControlEntInd>
      <PoliticalCampaignActyInd>false</PoliticalCampaignActyInd>
      <LobbyingActivitiesInd>false</LobbyingActivitiesInd>
      <SchoolOperatingInd>false</SchoolOperatingInd>
      <TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>false</TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>
      <PartVIOfCompOfHghstPdEmplTxt>NONE</PartVIOfCompOfHghstPdEmplTxt>
      <PartVIHghstPdCntrctProfSrvcTxt>NONE</PartVIHghstPdCntrctProfSrvcTxt>
      <FiledScheduleAInd>true</FiledScheduleAInd>
    </IRS990EZ>
    <IRS990ScheduleA documentId="RetDoc5">
      <PublicOrganization170Ind>X</PublicOrganization170Ind>
      <GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>65654</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>73143</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>53928</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>90801</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>57798</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>341324</TotalAmt>
      </GiftsGrantsContriRcvd170Grp>
      <TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>65654</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>73143</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>53928</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>90801</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>57798</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>341324</TotalAmt>
      </TotalCalendarYear170Grp>
      <SubstantialContributorsTotAmt>281781</SubstantialContributorsTotAmt>
      <PublicSupportTotal170Amt>59543</PublicSupportTotal170Amt>
      <TotalSupportAmt>341324</TotalSupportAmt>
      <PublicSupportCY170Pct>0.17440</PublicSupportCY170Pct>
      <PublicSupportPY170Pct>0.20780</PublicSupportPY170Pct>
      <TenPctFactsCrcmstncsTestCYInd>X</TenPctFactsCrcmstncsTestCYInd>
      <FactsAndCircumstancesTestTxt>FACTS-AND-CIRCUMSTANCES TEST: THE ORGANIZATION MAINTAINS AN ACTIVE, CONTINUOUS AND BONA FIDE FUNDRAISING PROGRAM DESIGNED TO ATTRACT NEW AND ADDITIONAL PUBLIC AND GOVERNMENTAL SUPPORT. IN AN EFFORT TO GENERATE PUBLIC SUPPORT, THE ORGANIZATION SENDS OUT AN ANNUAL LETTER TO SOLICIT DONATIONS. IN ADDITION, THE FOUNDATION ALSO ANNUALLY SENDS AN E-MAIL REQUESTING DONATIONS TO ALL OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SIGNED UP TO RECEIVE THE ORGANIZATION'S ELECTRONIC NEWSLETTER. THE ORGANIZATION ALSO MAINTAINS A FACEBOOK GROUP CALLED "HUICHOL CULTURAL SURVIVAL" WHICH IS NOW FOLLOWED BY MORE THAN 4,200 PEOPLE, INCLUDING A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. THEY POST NEWS ARTICLES ALMOST DAILY, VIDEOS, AND SHORT FILMS OF INTEREST. THE POSTS ARE OFTEN COMMENTED ON AND SHARED WHICH IN TURN BRINGS NEW PEOPLE TO THE GROUP. FINALLY, THE ORGANIZATION'S WEBSITE OFFERS EDUCATIONAL PUBLICATIONS, GREETING CARDS, AND T-SHIRTS IN EXCHANGE FOR DONATIONS. ALTHOUGH DURING THE 2017 TAX YEAR, THE MAJORITY OF THE ORGANIZATION'S SUPPORT CAME FROM ONE VERY GENEROUS INDIVIDUAL, THE ORGANIZATION HAS A BASE OF YEARLY DONORS THAT IS GROWING. THE ORGANIZATION ALSO COUNTS ON A GREAT DEAL OF NON-MONETARY SUPPORT IN THE WAY OF TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, COMPUTER MAINTENANCE, LEGAL ADVICE, HELP WITH TRANSLATING AND EDITING, REPORTING FROM NGO'S IN THE FIELD AND WIXRIKA PROFESSIONALS AND ELECTED AUTHORITIES WHO KEEP THE ORGANIZATION CURRENT ON EVENTS TAKING PLACE IN MEXICO. THE ORGANIZATION AIMS TO KEEP ACCESS TO THEIR WEBSITE FREE TO THE PUBLIC AND THE IN-KIND DONATIONS ARE THEREFORE OF SIGNIFICANT IMPORTANCE TO THE ORGANIZATION. COMPOSITION OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS: THE FOUNDERS AND BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE FOUNDATION CONTINUE TO ALL BE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN INTERESTED IN OR DEEPLY INVOLVED WITH THE WIXRIKA NATION FOR MANY DECADES. JUAN NEGRN, DIRECTOR AND FOUNDER OF THE WIXARIKA RESEARCH CENTER, HAS WORKED IN THE FIELD FOR 44 YEARS AND FOUNDED AND HEADED THREE NGO'S BENEFITING THE WIXRIKA IN MEXICO PRIOR TO RETURNING TO LIVE IN THE UNITED STATES IN 1996. TWO OF THESE NGO'S CONTINUE TO OPERATE PROVIDING IMPORTANT SERVICES TO THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. UNFORTUNATELY, ON AUGUST 28, 2015, OUR CO-FOUNDER AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR, JUAN NEGRN PASSED AWAY AFTER A YEARLONG STRUGGLE WITH EPILEPSY. AT OUR MEETING OF THE BOARD IN APRIL 2016, IT WAS DECIDED THAT JUAN'S WIFE AND CO-FOUNDER OF THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER, YVONNE NEGRN, WOULD TAKE OVER AS EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR. YVONNE NEGRN, WAS ACTIVE IN THE FIELD FROM 1970 THROUGH 1996 AND ACTIVELY WORKED WITH FOUR NGO'S IN MEXICO DURING THAT TIME. SHE CONTINUES TO MAKE TRIPS TO MEXICO FROM TIME TO TIME AND IS IN CONSTANT COMMUNICATION WITH THE WIXRIKA AND COLLEAGUES IN THE FIELD. IT IS HER TASK TO KEEP THE WEBSITE NEWS SECTION CURRENT AND TO BUILD NEW PAGES OF EXHIBITS OF FINE AND TRADITIONAL ART. SHE ALSO HANDLES MUCH OF THE COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE FOUNDATION. DR. DIANA NEGRN, PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS, IS A PHD FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BERKELEY - DEPARTMENT OF GEOGRAPHY AND A FORD FELLOW AND BANCROFT SCHOLAR. SHE COMPLETED A TWO YEAR POST DOCTORAL FELLOWSHIP AT THE CENTER FOR THE INVESTIGATION AND STUDY OF SOCIAL ANTHROPOLOGY IN GUADALAJARA, MEXICO IN MARCH, 2016. DIANA WAS RAISED FROM BIRTH AROUND THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND THE FOCUS OF HER DOCTORAL WORK IN HUMAN GEOGRAPHY IS ON WIXRIKA MIGRATIONS, HOW THEY ARE INTEGRATING INTO MEXICO'S URBAN AREAS AS STUDENTS SEEKING A HIGHER EDUCATION, AND THE DIFFICULTIES THEY ENCOUNTER. DIANA HAS SPENT AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF HOURS EACH MONTH MAKING CONTACT WITH OTHER FOUNDATIONS, SUCH AS THE INTERNATIONAL UNION FOR THE CONSERVATION OF NATURE, AND CONTINUES TO SPEND SIGNIFICANT TIME EACH MONTH TRANSLATING DOCUMENTS AND WRITING LETTERS FOR THE FOUNDATION. ANTHONY SOMKIN, M.D., TREASURER, HAS GIVEN SUBSTANTIAL TIME TO SCANNING COLOR SLIDES, REVIEWING THE FINANCIALS OF THE FOUNDATION, AND MAKING CONTACT WITH DONORS. ANTHONY ALSO ACTIVELY REACHES OUT TO PEOPLE IN AN EFFORT TO BRING IN FUNDING AND DID MUCH TO ORGANIZE THE EVENT AT THE LA PEA CULTURAL CENTER. HE HAS TRAVELED TO THE SIERRAS WHERE THE WIXRIKA HAVE THEIR HOMELAND ON TWO OCCASIONS AND HAS BEEN INTERESTED IN THEIR CULTURAL SURVIVAL SINCE THE MID 1970'S. STEPHEN ALDRICH WAS THE DIRECTOR OF FRIENDS OF HUICHOL CULTURE, BASED IN CAMBRIDGE, MA AND COLLABORATED WITH THE NEGRNS AND THEIR MEXICAN FOUNDATION ADESMO IN THE 1980'S. HE WAS ACTIVE IN ARRANGING EXHIBITS OF WIXRIKA ART AND SCHEDULING THE LECTURES AND SLIDE PRESENTATIONS GIVEN BY JUAN NEGRN AT HARVARD UNIVERSITY AND OTHER VENUES. DR. MARIA CRUZ, BOARD MEMEBER, IS A PHD. IN ANTHROPOLOGY FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS - AUSTIN CAMPUS AND IS A FELLOW WITH THE NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION. SHE IS THE ASSISTANT DIRECTOR OF MCNAIR SCHOLARS AT SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY, SAN JOSE, CALIFORNIA. HER GRANDFATHER WAS WIXRIKA FROM THE COMMUNITY OF SANTA CATARINA (TUAPURIE) WHICH GIVES HER A SPECIAL INTEREST IN THE WORK OF THE WIXARIKA RESEARCH CENTER. MARIA PARTICIPATES DOING EDITING AND COLLABORATING ON PROJECTS.</FactsAndCircumstancesTestTxt>
      <Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART II, LINE 17A</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>FACTS-AND-CIRCUMSTANCES TEST: THE ORGANIZATION MAINTAINS AN ACTIVE, CONTINUOUS AND BONA FIDE FUNDRAISING PROGRAM DESIGNED TO ATTRACT NEW AND ADDITIONAL PUBLIC AND GOVERNMENTAL SUPPORT. IN AN EFFORT TO GENERATE PUBLIC SUPPORT, THE ORGANIZATION SENDS OUT AN ANNUAL LETTER TO SOLICIT DONATIONS. IN ADDITION, THE FOUNDATION ALSO ANNUALLY SENDS AN E-MAIL REQUESTING DONATIONS TO ALL OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SIGNED UP TO RECEIVE THE ORGANIZATION'S ELECTRONIC NEWSLETTER. THE ORGANIZATION ALSO MAINTAINS A FACEBOOK GROUP CALLED "HUICHOL CULTURAL SURVIVAL" WHICH IS NOW FOLLOWED BY MORE THAN 4,200 PEOPLE, INCLUDING A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. THEY POST NEWS ARTICLES ALMOST DAILY, VIDEOS, AND SHORT FILMS OF INTEREST. THE POSTS ARE OFTEN COMMENTED ON AND SHARED WHICH IN TURN BRINGS NEW PEOPLE TO THE GROUP. FINALLY, THE ORGANIZATION'S WEBSITE OFFERS EDUCATIONAL PUBLICATIONS, GREETING CARDS, AND T-SHIRTS IN EXCHANGE FOR DONATIONS. ALTHOUGH DURING THE 2017 TAX YEAR, THE MAJORITY OF THE ORGANIZATION'S SUPPORT CAME FROM ONE VERY GENEROUS INDIVIDUAL, THE ORGANIZATION HAS A BASE OF YEARLY DONORS THAT IS GROWING. THE ORGANIZATION ALSO COUNTS ON A GREAT DEAL OF NON-MONETARY SUPPORT IN THE WAY OF TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE, COMPUTER MAINTENANCE, LEGAL ADVICE, HELP WITH TRANSLATING AND EDITING, REPORTING FROM NGO'S IN THE FIELD AND WIXRIKA PROFESSIONALS AND ELECTED AUTHORITIES WHO KEEP THE ORGANIZATION CURRENT ON EVENTS TAKING PLACE IN MEXICO. THE ORGANIZATION AIMS TO KEEP ACCESS TO THEIR WEBSITE FREE TO THE PUBLIC AND THE IN-KIND DONATIONS ARE THEREFORE OF SIGNIFICANT IMPORTANCE TO THE ORGANIZATION. COMPOSITION OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS: THE FOUNDERS AND BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF THE FOUNDATION CONTINUE TO ALL BE PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN INTERESTED IN OR DEEPLY INVOLVED WITH THE WIXRIKA NATION FOR MANY DECADES. JUAN NEGRN, DIRECTOR AND FOUNDER OF THE WIXARIKA RESEARCH CENTER, HAS WORKED IN THE FIELD FOR 44 YEARS AND FOUNDED AND HEADED THREE NGO'S BENEFITING THE WIXRIKA IN MEXICO PRIOR TO RETURNING TO LIVE IN THE UNITED STATES IN 1996. TWO OF THESE NGO'S CONTINUE TO OPERATE PROVIDING IMPORTANT SERVICES TO THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. UNFORTUNATELY, ON AUGUST 28, 2015, OUR CO-FOUNDER AND EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR, JUAN NEGRN PASSED AWAY AFTER A YEARLONG STRUGGLE WITH EPILEPSY. AT OUR MEETING OF THE BOARD IN APRIL 2016, IT WAS DECIDED THAT JUAN'S WIFE AND CO-FOUNDER OF THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER, YVONNE NEGRN, WOULD TAKE OVER AS EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR. YVONNE NEGRN, WAS ACTIVE IN THE FIELD FROM 1970 THROUGH 1996 AND ACTIVELY WORKED WITH FOUR NGO'S IN MEXICO DURING THAT TIME. SHE CONTINUES TO MAKE TRIPS TO MEXICO FROM TIME TO TIME AND IS IN CONSTANT COMMUNICATION WITH THE WIXRIKA AND COLLEAGUES IN THE FIELD. IT IS HER TASK TO KEEP THE WEBSITE NEWS SECTION CURRENT AND TO BUILD NEW PAGES OF EXHIBITS OF FINE AND TRADITIONAL ART. SHE ALSO HANDLES MUCH OF THE COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE FOUNDATION. DR. DIANA NEGRN, PRESIDENT OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS, IS A PHD FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA BERKELEY - DEPARTMENT OF GEOGRAPHY AND A FORD FELLOW AND BANCROFT SCHOLAR. SHE COMPLETED A TWO YEAR POST DOCTORAL FELLOWSHIP AT THE CENTER FOR THE INVESTIGATION AND STUDY OF SOCIAL ANTHROPOLOGY IN GUADALAJARA, MEXICO IN MARCH, 2016. DIANA WAS RAISED FROM BIRTH AROUND THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND THE FOCUS OF HER DOCTORAL WORK IN HUMAN GEOGRAPHY IS ON WIXRIKA MIGRATIONS, HOW THEY ARE INTEGRATING INTO MEXICO'S URBAN AREAS AS STUDENTS SEEKING A HIGHER EDUCATION, AND THE DIFFICULTIES THEY ENCOUNTER. DIANA HAS SPENT AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF HOURS EACH MONTH MAKING CONTACT WITH OTHER FOUNDATIONS, SUCH AS THE INTERNATIONAL UNION FOR THE CONSERVATION OF NATURE, AND CONTINUES TO SPEND SIGNIFICANT TIME EACH MONTH TRANSLATING DOCUMENTS AND WRITING LETTERS FOR THE FOUNDATION. ANTHONY SOMKIN, M.D., TREASURER, HAS GIVEN SUBSTANTIAL TIME TO SCANNING COLOR SLIDES, REVIEWING THE FINANCIALS OF THE FOUNDATION, AND MAKING CONTACT WITH DONORS. ANTHONY ALSO ACTIVELY REACHES OUT TO PEOPLE IN AN EFFORT TO BRING IN FUNDING AND DID MUCH TO ORGANIZE THE EVENT AT THE LA PEA CULTURAL CENTER. HE HAS TRAVELED TO THE SIERRAS WHERE THE WIXRIKA HAVE THEIR HOMELAND ON TWO OCCASIONS AND HAS BEEN INTERESTED IN THEIR CULTURAL SURVIVAL SINCE THE MID 1970'S. STEPHEN ALDRICH WAS THE DIRECTOR OF FRIENDS OF HUICHOL CULTURE, BASED IN CAMBRIDGE, MA AND COLLABORATED WITH THE NEGRNS AND THEIR MEXICAN FOUNDATION ADESMO IN THE 1980'S. HE WAS ACTIVE IN ARRANGING EXHIBITS OF WIXRIKA ART AND SCHEDULING THE LECTURES AND SLIDE PRESENTATIONS GIVEN BY JUAN NEGRN AT HARVARD UNIVERSITY AND OTHER VENUES. DR. MARIA CRUZ, BOARD MEMEBER, IS A PHD. IN ANTHROPOLOGY FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS - AUSTIN CAMPUS AND IS A FELLOW WITH THE NATIONAL SCIENCE FOUNDATION. SHE IS THE ASSISTANT DIRECTOR OF MCNAIR SCHOLARS AT SAN JOSE STATE UNIVERSITY, SAN JOSE, CALIFORNIA. HER GRANDFATHER WAS WIXRIKA FROM THE COMMUNITY OF SANTA CATARINA (TUAPURIE) WHICH GIVES HER A SPECIAL INTEREST IN THE WORK OF THE WIXARIKA RESEARCH CENTER. MARIA PARTICIPATES DOING EDITING AND COLLABORATING ON PROJECTS.</ExplanationTxt>
      </Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleA>
    <IRS990ScheduleB documentId="RetDoc1" />
    <IRS990ScheduleO documentId="RetDoc4">
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990-EZ, PART I, LINE 16</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>EXPENSES OFFICE EXPENSE 79 INTERNET 686 WEB HOSTING 299 COMPUTER EXPENSE 1,252 TRAVEL 972 BANK CHARGES 56 TELEPHONE 711 STATE REGISTRY 25 ARCHIVING PROJECT 2,075 EQUIPMENT 106 NON-INVESTMENT DEPRECIATION 3,500 TOTAL 9,761</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990-EZ, PART II, LINE 24</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>OTHER DEPRECIABLE ASSET 46,691 55,494 LESS ACCUMULATED DEPRECIATION 46,661 50,161 YARN PAINTINGS BY JOSE BENITEZ SANCH 23,750 22,505 TOTAL 23,780 27,838</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990-EZ, PART III</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>ADVOCACY FOR THE HUICHOL INDIANS IN MEXICO, AND PRESERVATION AND PROMOTION OF THE HUICHOL CULTURE AND ARTWORK.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990-EZ, PART III, LINE 28</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER MAINTAINS AN ONLINE WORLD-CLASS ARCHIVE OF WIXRIKA (HUICHOL) INDIGENOUS ART AND CULTURE TO EDUCATE THE PUBLIC ABOUT THIS UNIQUE AND EXTRAORDINARY CULTURE. THROUGH THE FOUNDATION'S WEB SITE, WE RAISE PUBLIC AWARENESS ABOUT THE CHALLENGES THESE INDIGENOUS PEOPLE ARE FACING TODAY DUE TO THEIR RAPIDLY CHANGING ENVIRONMENT. IT IS OUR HOPE THAT THE WEBSITE WILL AMPLIFY THEIR VOICES AND ADD WEIGHT TO THEIR OPINIONS AND CONCERNS. OUR WEBSITE, WHICH IS PUBLISHED IN ENGLISH AND SPANISH, GIVES THE PUBLIC FREE ACCESS TO IMAGES OF AN EXTRAORDINARY COLLECTION OF THEIR TRADITIONAL, SACRED, AND CONTEMPORARY ART AND PUBLISHES NEWS ON RELEVANT CURRENT EVENTS. WE ALSO MAINTAIN A FACEBOOK GROUP CALLED "HUICHOL CULTURAL SURVIVAL" WHICH IS NOW FOLLOWED BY MORE THAN 4,200 PEOPLE, INCLUDING A LARGE NUMBER OF PEOPLE FROM THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES. WE POST NEWS ARTICLES ALMOST DAILY, VIDEOS, AND SHORT FILMS OF INTEREST. OUR POSTS ARE OFTEN COMMENTED ON AND SHARED WHICH IN TURN BRINGS NEW PEOPLE TO OUR GROUP. THE WORK OF THE WIXRIKA RESEARCH CENTER (WRC) CONSISTS OF PRESERVING, IN DIGITAL FORMAT, PHOTOGRAPHS, DOCUMENTS, TAPE RECORDINGS AND IMAGES OF SACRED, TRADITIONAL, AND CONTEMPORARY ART, COLLECTED AND/OR PHOTOGRAPHED BY JUAN AND YVONNE NEGRIN FROM 1970 TO PRESENT. THE PAPER ARCHIVES BEING DIGITALIZED INCLUDE COPIES OF DOCUMENTS AND NEWS REPORTS PERTAINING TO PAST AND PRESENT LAND DISPUTES, THE EXPLOITATION OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE'S NATURAL RESOURCES, AND COMMUNITY DOCUMENTS AND PETITIONS DRAWN UP AT THEIR GENERAL ASSEMBLIES. HUNDREDS OF COLOR TRANSPARENCIES TAKEN BY JUAN &amp; YVONNE NEGRIN HAVE BEEN SCANNED IN HIGH RESOLUTION FOR PRESERVATION. THESE PHOTOGRAPHS ARE UNIQUE BECAUSE THE WIXRIKA COMMUNITIES RARELY PERMITTED CAMERAS TO BE USED TO CAPTURE THEIR WAY OF LIFE, THEIR CEREMONIES, OR THEIR SACRED SPOTS BY OUTSIDERS. AN EXCEPTION WAS MADE IN THE CASE OF THE NEGRNS BECAUSE OF THEIR DEDICATED WORK IN DEFENDING THE LAND AND RESOURCES OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND THE NON-PROFIT NATURE OF THE WORK THEY CARRIED OUT OVER SEVERAL DECADES. THIS IS AN ONGOING PROJECT EXPECTED TO TAKE SUBSTANTIAL TIME TO COMPLETE. THE TAPE RECORDINGS CONSIST OF SACRED CHANTS, ORAL HISTORY AS RECOUNTED BY MEMBERS OF THE COUNCIL OF ELDERS, TRADITIONAL MUSIC, COMMUNITY ASSEMBLIES AND INTERVIEWS. THE ORIGINAL RECORDINGS WERE MADE ON MAGNETIC CASSETTES AND THEIR CONVERSION TO DIGITAL FORMAT IS NECESSARY IN ORDER TO PRESERVE THIS IMPORTANT BODY OF WORK. IN AUGUST OF 2017, WE BEGAN TO DESIGN AND BUILD A LONG OVERDUE NEW WEBSITE AND ONLINE ARCHIVE THAT WILL ENABLE US TO PROVIDE ACCESS TO A LARGE BODY OF HISTORICAL DOCUMENTS, MORE ART EXHIBITS, AND A BETTER DESIGNED NEWS SECTION. IT WILL ALSO HAVE AN EFFICIENT SEARCH ENGINE TO AID THE PUBLIC IN FINDING WHAT THEY ARE LOOKING FOR. WE ESTIMATE THIS PROJECT WILL TAKE CLOSE TO A YEAR TO COMPLETE SINCE WE WILL BE DESIGNING EACH SECTION AS WE GO AND DUE TO THE LARGE BODY OF DOCUMENTS AND EXHIBITS TO BE TRANSFERRED FROM OUR OLD WEBSITE, AND THE MANY NEW DOCUMENTS AND NEWS ITEMS TO BE UPLOADED. THIS PROJECT HAS BEEN UNDERTAKEN BY YVONNE NEGRN WITH THE HELP OF OUR WEB MASTERS WES AND COLETTE HEADLEY OF ACTUAL SYSTEMS. WE ARE PLEASED AT THE PROSPECT OF FINALLY HAVING A WEBSITE THAT WILL BE MUCH MORE USER FRIENDLY, IS CAPABLE OF HANDLING A LARGE DATABASE OF DOCUMENTS, AND BETTER SUITS OUR FOUNDATION'S MISSION, THE NEEDS OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE, AND OUR AUDIENCE. IN SEPTEMBER, WE ENJOYED A NEARLY TWO-MONTH VISIT FROM AUKWE GARCA MIJAREZ, A YOUNG WIXRIKA WOMAN AND RECENT GRADUATE OF ITESO (INSTITUTO TECNOLOGICO DE ESTUDIOS SUPERIORES DE OCCIDENTE) THE JESUIT UNIVERSITY IN GUADALAJARA. AUKWE GRADUATED IN DECEMBER 2016 WITH A DEGREE IN COMMUNICATIONS AND IS THE DIRECTOR OF COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE REGIONAL WIXRIKA COUNCIL THAT IS IN CHARGE OF THE DEFENSE OF THEIR PEOPLES' SACRED LOCATIONS. DURING HER STAY SHE WAS ABLE TO LEARN MORE ABOUT THE WORK OUR FOUNDATION HAS BEEN DOING AND WAS ABLE TO VIEW AND STUDY MANY OF THE ARCHIVES COLLECTED BY JUAN NEGRN OVER HIS LIFETIME OF WORK WITH HER PEOPLE. IN PARTICULAR SHE FOCUSED ON ARCHIVES RELATING TO THE INVASION OF WIXRIKA TERRITORY BY THEIR NEIGHBORS, THE EXPLOITATION OF THEIR FORESTS, AND OTHER RELATED POLITICAL ARCHIVES. SHE TOOK THE TIME TO THOROUGHLY READ OVER ONE HUNDRED DOCUMENTS, MANY OF WHICH WERE MULTIPLE PAGES, SCAN THEM FOR FUTURE UPLOAD TO THE NEW WEBSITE, AND SHE ALSO CREATED AN EXCEL SHEET DESCRIBING THEIR CONTENT AND IMPORTANCE. LATER IN HER TRIP, SHE ATTENDED AND PARTICIPATED IN OUR MEETING OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS. AT THE MEETING SHE TOLD US THE DOCUMENTS WERE OF GREAT IMPORTANCE TO HER PEOPLE BECAUSE THEY TOLD THE WHOLE STORY OF HOW HER PEOPLE WERE EXPLOITED ONCE THE FIRST ROAD WAS BUILT IN THE EARLY 1970'S GIVING EASIER ACCESS TO THEIR TERRITORY BY OUTSIDE INTERESTS FOR THE FIRST TIME. SHE EMPHASIZED THAT THIS IS AN IMPORTANT STORY FOR HER PEOPLE TO KNOW SINCE THE YOUNGER GENERATION HAD NOT EVEN BEEN BORN YET. THESE DOCUMENTS WILL FORM A PART OF THE HISTORICAL ARCHIVE THAT WILL BE AVAILABLE ONLINE TO THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND TO ALL OTHERS INTERESTED IN LEARNING ABOUT THIS HISTORY. IN OCTOBER WE CO-HOSTED AN EVENT AT THE SAN FRANCISCO DE YOUNG MUSEUM WITH CINE Y MS. THE EVENT BEGAN WITH A SLIDE PRESENTATION HIGHLIGHTING THE TERRITORY, DAILY LIFE, SACRED PILGRIMAGES, AND CEREMONIES OF THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE AND WAS FOLLOWED BY A FILM "THE MARRAKAME'S DREAM" WHICH TOLD THE STORY OF A WIXRIKA HEALER AND HIS SON. AFTER THE FILM DIANA NEGRN AND AUKWE GARCA ANSWERED QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE. THE EVENT WAS VERY WELL RECEIVED BY THE PUBLIC AND IT GAVE THEM AN UNDERSTANDING OF THE CHALLENGES THE WIXRIKA PEOPLE FACE AS THEY STRUGGLE FOR THEIR CULTURAL SURVIVAL. IN MID-DECEMBER, MATSIWA, WHO IS A SPIRITUAL LEADER IN HIS COMMUNITY, CAME TO SPEND THE HOLIDAYS WITH US AND TO TELL US ABOUT THE DELIVERY OF PHOTOGRAPHS AND RECORDINGS HE HAD DELIVERED ON OUR BEHALF TO THE PEOPLE IN THE SIERRAS. ALL THE RECIPIENTS WERE THRILLED WE WERE ESPECIALLY HAPPY THAT THE ORAL HISTORY IS NOW IN THE HANDS OF THE FAMILIES OF THE ELDERS, WHICH IS NOW A PROMISE THAT HAS BEEN KEPT. OF COURSE THERE WERE REQUESTS FOR MORE PHOTOGRAPHS SO WE WILL DO SOME MORE PRINTING FOR THE FAMILY MEMBERS WHO WILL BE WAITING. IN LATE FEBRUARY 2018, DIANA NEGRN TRAVELLED TO MEXICO TO PARTICIPATE IN THE CONFERENCE ON THE SACRED PLANTS OF THE AMERICAS THAT WAS HELD IN AJIJIC ON LAKE CHAPALA. OUR FOUNDATION WAS ONE OF THE SPONSORS OF THE EVENT AND DIANA MODERATED A PANEL OF FIVE WIXRIKA PEOPLE ON THE SUBJECT OF THE EXPLOITATION OF THEIR SACRED PLACES AND SPECIFICALLY THE ONGOING THREAT OF MINING IN THE DESERT OF WIRIKUTA. THE PANEL CONSISTED OF A WIXRIKA LAWYER, THE HEAD OF COMMUNICATIONS FOR THE WIXRIKA REGIONAL COUNCIL FOR THE DEFENSE OF THEIR TERRITORIES, A SHAMAN AND SPIRITUAL LEADER, AND TWO OTHERS, A MAN AND A WOMAN, WHO ARE SPOKESPERSONS FOR THE DEFENSE OF THEIR CULTURE. THE ENTIRE CONFERENCE WAS FILMED AND WE HAVE POSTED VIDEOS ON OUR WEBSITE. DURING THIS FISCAL YEAR WE ALSO BEGAN WORK ON TWO FUTURE EXHIBITS. WE WERE CONTACTED BY TELEVISA THROUGH OUR WEBSITE AND ASKED TO PARTICIPATE IN THEIR EXHIBIT MEXICOLOR WHICH WILL OPEN AT THE PALACE OF FINE ARTS IN MEXICO CITY IN LATE MAY OF 2020. WE RECEIVED A VISIT FROM JOHN OLS, WHO IS CURATING THE EXHIBIT, AND HE CHOSE SIX PHOTOGRAPHS TAKEN OF THE WIXRIKA BY JUAN NEGRN. THREE WILL BE ON EXHIBIT AND ALL SIX WILL APPEAR IN THE BOOK BEING PUBLISHED TO ACCOMPANY THE EXHIBIT. THE SECOND EXHIBIT IS BEING CURATED BY OUR DIRECTOR, DIANA NEGRN, AND IS PLANNED TO OPEN AT THE INSTITUTO CULTURAL CABAAS IN GUADALAJARA AT THE END OF JUNE 2019. THIS EXHIBIT WILL BE MUCH MORE EXTENSIVE CONSISTING OF YARN PAINTINGS, TEXTILES, PHOTOGRAPHS, FILM, AND OF COURSE A CATALOGUE. THE EXHIBIT WILL TRAVEL TO OTHER MUSEUMS IN MEXICO AND HOPEFULLY THE TOUR CAN CLOSE AT A MUSEUM IN THE UNITED STATES. THIS SPRING WE WERE ALSO CONTACTED THROUGH OUR WEBSITE BY THE INTERNATIONAL FRIENDSHIP CLUB IN PUERTO VALLARTA. THIS IS A CLUB OF AMERICANS LIVING IN MEXICO WHO ARE INTERESTED IN HELPING WIXRIKA YOUTH WITH EDUCATIONAL EXPENSES. SINCE THEY ARE INCORPORATED IN MEXICO DONATIONS WILL HAVE TO BE GIVEN TO A FOUNDATION REGISTERED IN MEXICO BUT THEY HAVE ASSIGNED US THE TASK OF LOCATING A MEXICAN NON-PROFIT FOUNDATION WE CAN ALL WORK WITH. IT WILL BE UP TO US TO SCREEN STUDENTS, DELIVER THE SCHOLARSHIPS AND TO FOLLOW UP ON EACH STUDENT'S PROGRESS. WE HOPE THAT THE FIRST SCHOLARSHIPS CAN BE DELIVERED TO STUDENTS IN THE FALL OF 2018. FOR THIS FIRST YEAR, SIX SCHOLARSHIPS OF 5,000 PESOS (258 USD) EACH WILL BE GIVEN AND IF ALL WORKS WELL THE INTERNATIONAL FRIENDSHIP CLUB INTENDS TO EXPAND THE PROGRAM. NEEDLESS TO SAY WE ARE VERY HONORED AND EXCITED TO PARTICIPATE IN THE INITIATIVE TO PROVIDE ASSISTANCE TO DESERVING STUDENTS.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleO>
  </ReturnData>
</Return>