<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Return>
  <ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCnt="0">
    <ReturnTs>2019-02-14T22:49:23-07:00</ReturnTs>
    <TaxPeriodEndDt>2018-12-31</TaxPeriodEndDt>
    <ReturnTypeCd>990EZ</ReturnTypeCd>
    <TaxPeriodBeginDt>2018-01-01</TaxPeriodBeginDt>
    <Filer>
      <EIN>042726186</EIN>
      <BusinessName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>SUSILA DHARMA USA INC</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </BusinessName>
      <BusinessNameControlTxt>SUSI</BusinessNameControlTxt>
      <PhoneNum>6503538714</PhoneNum>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>1196 Holmes Court</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>Livermore</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>CA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>94550</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
    </Filer>
    <BusinessOfficerGrp>
      <PersonNm>Humphrey Williams</PersonNm>
      <PersonTitleTxt>Treasurer</PersonTitleTxt>
      <PhoneNum>6504940364</PhoneNum>
      <SignatureDt>2019-02-14</SignatureDt>
    </BusinessOfficerGrp>
    <FilingSecurityInformation>
      <IPAddress>
        <IPv4AddressTxt>173.228.124.165</IPv4AddressTxt>
      </IPAddress>
    </FilingSecurityInformation>
    <TaxYr>2018</TaxYr>
    <BuildTS>2019-02-21 02:37:17Z</BuildTS>
  </ReturnHeader>
  <ReturnData documentCnt="4">
    <IRS990EZ documentId="R000001" referenceDocumentId="R000004" softwareId="18007995" softwareVersionNum="v1.00">
      <MethodOfAccountingCashInd>X</MethodOfAccountingCashInd>
      <WebsiteAddressTxt>susiladharmausa.org</WebsiteAddressTxt>
      <Organization501c3Ind referenceDocumentId="R000002">X</Organization501c3Ind>
      <TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>X</TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>
      <GrossReceiptsAmt>112509</GrossReceiptsAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIInd>
      <ContributionsGiftsGrantsEtcAmt>106394</ContributionsGiftsGrantsEtcAmt>
      <ProgramServiceRevenueAmt>0</ProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <MembershipDuesAmt>0</MembershipDuesAmt>
      <InvestmentIncomeAmt>6115</InvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <SaleOfAssetsGrossAmt>0</SaleOfAssetsGrossAmt>
      <CostOrOtherBasisExpenseSaleAmt>0</CostOrOtherBasisExpenseSaleAmt>
      <GainOrLossFromSaleOfAssetsAmt>0</GainOrLossFromSaleOfAssetsAmt>
      <GamingGrossIncomeAmt>0</GamingGrossIncomeAmt>
      <FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt fndrsngEventContriPrevRptAmt="0">0</FundraisingGrossIncomeAmt>
      <SpecialEventsDirectExpensesAmt>0</SpecialEventsDirectExpensesAmt>
      <SpecialEventsNetIncomeLossAmt>0</SpecialEventsNetIncomeLossAmt>
      <GrossSalesOfInventoryAmt>0</GrossSalesOfInventoryAmt>
      <CostOfGoodsSoldAmt>0</CostOfGoodsSoldAmt>
      <GrossProfitLossSlsOfInvntryAmt>0</GrossProfitLossSlsOfInvntryAmt>
      <OtherRevenueTotalAmt>0</OtherRevenueTotalAmt>
      <TotalRevenueAmt>112509</TotalRevenueAmt>
      <GrantsAndSimilarAmountsPaidAmt>98813</GrantsAndSimilarAmountsPaidAmt>
      <BenefitsPaidToOrForMembersAmt>0</BenefitsPaidToOrForMembersAmt>
      <SalariesOtherCompEmplBnftAmt>0</SalariesOtherCompEmplBnftAmt>
      <FeesAndOtherPymtToIndCntrctAmt>3590</FeesAndOtherPymtToIndCntrctAmt>
      <OccupancyRentUtltsAndMaintAmt>2926</OccupancyRentUtltsAndMaintAmt>
      <PrintingPublicationsPostageAmt>2134</PrintingPublicationsPostageAmt>
      <OtherExpensesTotalAmt>9509</OtherExpensesTotalAmt>
      <TotalExpensesAmt>116972</TotalExpensesAmt>
      <ExcessOrDeficitForYearAmt>-4463</ExcessOrDeficitForYearAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>332941</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>
      <OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>2171</OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>330649</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>
      <CashSavingsAndInvestmentsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>332941</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>330649</EOYAmt>
      </CashSavingsAndInvestmentsGrp>
      <LandAndBuildingsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>0</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>0</EOYAmt>
      </LandAndBuildingsGrp>
      <OtherAssetsTotalDetail>
        <BOYAmt>0</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>0</EOYAmt>
      </OtherAssetsTotalDetail>
      <Form990TotalAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>332941</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>330649</EOYAmt>
      </Form990TotalAssetsGrp>
      <SumOfTotalLiabilitiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>0</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>0</EOYAmt>
      </SumOfTotalLiabilitiesGrp>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>332941</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>330649</EOYAmt>
      </NetAssetsOrFundBalancesGrp>
      <PrimaryExemptPurposeTxt>Endorses capacity building activities that are locally initiated and committed to serving local populations through interactive participation and collaborative partnerships. We view humanitarian service as participatory: when people give to other people, mutually transforming relationships occur.</PrimaryExemptPurposeTxt>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Dem Republic of Congo Community Health Center. $210 to support local health centers</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>210</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Elderberry is a program to support elder members to go to places of worship</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>1000</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>International Child Development is based on principles that are in line with the UN Convention on the Rights of the Child. ICDP participates directly and indirectly in activities run by other humanitarian organisations that have corresponding objectives. The ICDP is another expression of the same humanitarian spirit as it is encoded in the convention of children' rights. ICDP's methods can be put in practice in any community to create positive conditions for the fulfilment of fundamental children's rights: the right to be protected from violence and to receive the loving care and guidance from the immediate environment which is required to ensure healthy human development. Introducing children's rights is likely to have a major impact on families (and all levels of authorities) if efforts are also made to activate awareness and deeper bonding to children as persons.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>1835</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>The Inner City Schools project provides art supplies and books that are not normally available to children in low income schools. The project currently supports four schools, with supplies delivered every month. In addition the project provides clothing for homeless children when requested by social services in the area.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>3500</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Quest Center for Integrative Health is a wellness-focused, nonprofit healthcare clinic striving to strengthen those diagnosed with chronic or life challenging illness. Quest is committed to treating everyone, including low-income, medically underserved people, many of whom are living with HIV/AIDS, cancer and behavioral health disorders. Quest, founded in Portland, Oregon, by Lusijah Marx in 1989, focuses on providing healthy meals, alternative therapies, and nutrition education.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>2000</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Subud San Diego provides community development funds to a community in Tijuana Mexico</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>1743</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Usaha Mulia Abadi A.C. focuses on the following different areas: Infrastructure: Build a center for an educational program focused on children and youth. Nutrition: Pack and deliver nutritional products to children. The products contain proteins, vitamins and minerals to support a child's daily nutrition. Workshops for children: Develop children's skills and talents through art. Social service: Activities for the community of San Miguel Atlautla (elder people, children's day, Christmas, etc.) Ecology: Reforestation, forest cleaning and care of the orchard. Ecotourist project: Create a space to be in contact with nature, to learn from it and to learn how to take care of it. Social Service: We have had very nice activities with elder people and celebrated children's day and Christmas. We have collected food, clothes and toys and delivered them with success. Ecology: They have reforested the area and 97% of the trees have survived. We have also cleaned the forest in order to provide fires and we have had a positive reaction from the community</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>2743</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>A Child's Garden of Peace is a collaborative effort founded and directed by Dr. Illene Pevec to create gardens where children can play in peace and learn to grow food for themselves and their families. ACGP acts always in collaboration with other educational entities and foundations.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>1835</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Yayasan Permakultur Kalimantan (YPK) has been established in Central Kalimantan, Indonesia, to support the resilience and empowerment of individuals and communities to return to long term sustainable agriculture, livelihoods and culture through the provision of integrated, community-centred, culturally-appropriate education, training and programs.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>3670</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Yayasan Tambuhak Sinta (YTS)YTS began working in the seven villages of Bukit Batu in 2009. Using participatory rural appraisal techniques, we assisted each community in the sub-district to make a village development plan, and started providing an annual village development fund to support local livelihoods. The project has identified two livelihood opportunities that show much promise for the development of successful micro-enterprises, these are fish-farming and chicken-raising. In both cases, profitability is limited by the high cost of material inputs, primarily for feed. To overcome this barrier, YTS wishes to provide strategic support to the seven communities by providing training and equipment to manufacture feed from local sources.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4588</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Yayasan Usaha Mulia (YUM) YUM is an umbrella charity that oversees various Indonesian initiatives, including, orphanages, schools operating in slum areas, provision of food, microcredit, supplies, and education to families in crisis, technical and educational assistence to provide clean water and organic produce.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>9385</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Anisha Anisha's work is focussed on rural areas of India, specifically in the state of Karnataka, in an effort create a sustainable economic and environmental model for villagers and to slow the flight of families from impoverished areas in the countryside into the hugely overcrowded urban areas. Anisha project began in 1998 in the slums of Bangalore City</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>25497</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>The Mission of Bina Cita Utama (BCU) School is to be an innovative educational community in the Palangka Raya district of Central Kalimantan, offering challenging programs of study and a high-quality environment for learning. BCU seeks to nurture individuality, self-worth, a sense of humanity, and to educate children to become adults who will make a positive contribution to the development of their communities and the world.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4588</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Camp Badger.Founded in 2004, Camp Badger's arts and enrichment activities serve children of California's Fresno and Tulare County Sierra foothills and nearby San Joaquin Valley towns. These programs help kids tap their innate resourcefulness and encourage them to take creative risks through individual and collaborative artistic expression. Camp Badger is fiscally sponsored by Seven Circles Retreat in Badger, California, a 501(c) (3) nonprofit corporation, along with Susila Dharma USA.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>2794</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Borneo Football International Academy provides a healthy environment and quality assistance to children and youth in Kalimantan.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4300</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Casa Luna (Casa Cuna) is a preschool in Puebla, Mexico. Money was given to increase Teacher Salaries.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>1000</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Wawa Illari Pachacamac, Peru: high rates of poverty, domestic violence, malnutrition, child abuse and neglect mean that the children of this community are at a distinct disadvantage. Families in Pachacamac often live with inadequate water/sanitation, poor hygiene and limited access to nutritious foods leading to dietary deficiencies and malnutrition.All this makes it a pretty bad place to live, but a good example of an environment that can put at risk healthy brain development in small children</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4000</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>I Protect Me: They have worked since 2013 in schools in Cape Town to teach children how to protect themselves from sexual and gender-based violence. They use the methodology of Kenya's Dolphin Anti-Rape and Aids Outreach. To teach the children in primary school how to protect and defend themselves, skills are taught through song, dance and storytelling. In many incidents of sexual abuse amongst older children, the perpetrators were other children, peers.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4588</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>The Venezuela Food Connection is a relief effort intended to addresses the severe food shortage that exists in Venezuela due to economic and political instability. The project brings relief to Caracas and surrounding area. The project serves at present an estimated 85 people in severe need. Food is purchased in USA and shipped direct to Venezuela.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4352</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Funds have been allocated to send an overseas project director to the Subud World congress so that they may present their project to a wide global community.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>2250</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>THE SUSILA DHARMA INTERNATIONAL ASSOCIATION (SDIA) is a network of SD national organizations and associate member projects from 23 countries. We believe that by working together in an atmosphere of mutual respect we can achieve positive social and economic change that benefits our world.SDIA builds the capacity of our members to develop and sustain their organizations and projects. We provide training and coordinate technical, financial and human resources. We build connections with donors and provide communication and information-sharing services. SDIA promotes awareness of key issues such as gender equality, child rights, healthcare, sustainable livelihoods, and innovative and effective development practices.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>7340</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>THE WOMEN WORLDWIDE INITIATIVE: This Mentorship Program is an educational, leadership and personal development program for adolescent girls living in low-income, under-served urban communities that serve 30 girls (ages 14 - 18) and 30 young women (ages 21 - 35) next year. The program is curriculum, group and one-on-one based, pairing college students and young professional women with teenage girls. The mission of the program is to empower girls through mentorship, building their self-confidence and challenging them to discover and fulfill their potential.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>4588</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>Borneo Orangutan Survival (BOS) Foundation is an Indonesian non-profit organization dedicated to the conservation of the Bornean orangutan and its habitat, in cooperation with local communities, the Indonesian Ministry of Forestry and international partner organizations. BOS Foundation is currently taking care of almost 650 orangutans with the support of 400 highly devoted staff, as well as experts in primatology, biodiversity, ecology, forest rehabilitation, agroforestry, community empowerment, education, and orangutan healthcare.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>506</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ForeignGrantsInd>X</ForeignGrantsInd>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
        <DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>"Misfit Samaritans", is part of a larger group titled "Free Hot Soup". These groups provide meals for the homeless and impoverished population of Portland, OR.</DescriptionProgramSrvcAccomTxt>
        <GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>500</GrantsAndAllocationsAmt>
        <ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</ProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      </ProgramSrvcAccomplishmentGrp>
      <TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>0</TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Aminah Herrman</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Chair</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>5</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Humphrey Williams</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Treasurer</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>5</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Elisa Sunflower</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>2</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>fauziyah Sue Ishak</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>2</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Jake Sterling</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>5</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Laurie Lathrop</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Director</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>2</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>Marilyn Schirk</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>Board Advisor</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>2</AverageHrsPerWkDevotedToPosRt>
        <CompensationAmt>0</CompensationAmt>
        <EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>0</EmployeeBenefitProgramAmt>
        <ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>0</ExpenseAccountOtherAllwncAmt>
      </OfficerDirectorTrusteeEmplGrp>
      <ActivitiesNotPreviouslyRptInd>0</ActivitiesNotPreviouslyRptInd>
      <ChgMadeToOrgnzngDocNotRptInd>0</ChgMadeToOrgnzngDocNotRptInd>
      <OrganizationHadUBIInd>0</OrganizationHadUBIInd>
      <SubjectToProxyTaxInd>0</SubjectToProxyTaxInd>
      <OrganizationDissolvedEtcInd>0</OrganizationDissolvedEtcInd>
      <DirectIndirectPltclExpendAmt>0</DirectIndirectPltclExpendAmt>
      <Form1120PolFiledInd>0</Form1120PolFiledInd>
      <MadeLoansToFromOfficersInd>0</MadeLoansToFromOfficersInd>
      <TaxImposedUnderIRC4911Amt>0</TaxImposedUnderIRC4911Amt>
      <TaxImposedUnderIRC4912Amt>0</TaxImposedUnderIRC4912Amt>
      <TaxImposedUnderIRC4955Amt>0</TaxImposedUnderIRC4955Amt>
      <EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>0</EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <TaxImposedOnOrganizationMgrAmt>0</TaxImposedOnOrganizationMgrAmt>
      <TaxReimbursedByOrganizationAmt>0</TaxReimbursedByOrganizationAmt>
      <ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>0</ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>CA</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>MA</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>MD</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <BooksInCareOfDetail>
        <PersonNm>Humphrey Williams</PersonNm>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1196 Holmes Court</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>Livermore</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>CA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>94550</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <PhoneNum>6504940364</PhoneNum>
      </BooksInCareOfDetail>
      <ForeignFinancialAccountInd>0</ForeignFinancialAccountInd>
      <ForeignOfficeInd>0</ForeignOfficeInd>
      <DonorAdvisedFndsInd>0</DonorAdvisedFndsInd>
      <OperateHospitalInd>0</OperateHospitalInd>
      <TanningServicesProvidedInd>0</TanningServicesProvidedInd>
      <RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>0</RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>
      <TransactionWithControlEntInd>0</TransactionWithControlEntInd>
      <PoliticalCampaignActyInd>0</PoliticalCampaignActyInd>
      <LobbyingActivitiesInd>0</LobbyingActivitiesInd>
      <SchoolOperatingInd>0</SchoolOperatingInd>
      <TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>0</TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>
      <PartVIOfCompOfHghstPdEmplTxt>NONE</PartVIOfCompOfHghstPdEmplTxt>
      <PartVIHghstPdCntrctProfSrvcTxt>NONE</PartVIHghstPdCntrctProfSrvcTxt>
      <FiledScheduleAInd>1</FiledScheduleAInd>
    </IRS990EZ>
    <IRS990ScheduleA documentId="R000002" softwareId="18007995" softwareVersionNum="v1.00">
      <PubliclySupportedOrg509a2Ind>X</PubliclySupportedOrg509a2Ind>
      <GiftsGrantsContrisRcvd509Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>128775</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>113720</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>74825</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>128638</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>106395</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>552353</TotalAmt>
      </GiftsGrantsContrisRcvd509Grp>
      <Total509Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>128775</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>113720</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>74825</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>128638</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>106395</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>552353</TotalAmt>
      </Total509Grp>
      <PublicSupportTotal509Amt>552353</PublicSupportTotal509Amt>
      <GrossInvestmentIncome509Grp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>9645</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>3264</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>5021</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>3972</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>6115</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>28017</TotalAmt>
      </GrossInvestmentIncome509Grp>
      <InvestmentIncomeAndUBTIGrp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>9645</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>3264</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>5021</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>3972</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>6115</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>28017</TotalAmt>
      </InvestmentIncomeAndUBTIGrp>
      <TotalSupportCalendarYearGrp>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>138420</CurrentTaxYearMinus4YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>116984</CurrentTaxYearMinus3YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>79846</CurrentTaxYearMinus2YearsAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>132610</CurrentTaxYearMinus1YearAmt>
        <CurrentTaxYearAmt>112510</CurrentTaxYearAmt>
        <TotalAmt>580370</TotalAmt>
      </TotalSupportCalendarYearGrp>
      <PublicSupportCY509Pct>0.95173</PublicSupportCY509Pct>
      <PublicSupportPY509Pct>0.94409</PublicSupportPY509Pct>
      <InvestmentIncomeCYPct>0.04827</InvestmentIncomeCYPct>
      <InvestmentIncomePYPct>0.05591</InvestmentIncomePYPct>
      <ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsPY509Ind>X</ThirtyThrPctSuprtTestsPY509Ind>
    </IRS990ScheduleA>
    <IRS990ScheduleB documentId="R000003" softwareId="18007995" softwareVersionNum="v1.00" />
    <IRS990ScheduleO documentId="R000004" softwareId="18007995" softwareVersionNum="v1.00">
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990-EZ, Part I, Line 16</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>Description;Amount^Bank Charges;27|Computers Software and Web;409|Credit Card Fees and related expenses;596|Governance Filing and insurance;56|Shipping;62|Meetings and Travel;8078|Wire Fees;281^Total;9509^</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>Form 990-EZ, Part I, Line 20</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>Description;Amount^Adjustment for funds in flight at year end;1225|Additional Endowment Fund growth;946^Total;2171^</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleO>
  </ReturnData>
</Return>