<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Return>
  <ReturnHeader binaryAttachmentCnt="0">
    <ReturnTs>2019-01-08T13:43:04-06:00</ReturnTs>
    <TaxPeriodEndDt>2018-06-30</TaxPeriodEndDt>
    <PreparerFirmGrp>
      <PreparerFirmEIN>390859910</PreparerFirmEIN>
      <PreparerFirmName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>BAKER TILLY VIRCHOW KRAUSE LLP</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </PreparerFirmName>
      <PreparerUSAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>1650 MARKET STREET SUITE 4500</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>PHILADELPHIA</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>191037341</ZIPCd>
      </PreparerUSAddress>
    </PreparerFirmGrp>
    <ReturnTypeCd>990</ReturnTypeCd>
    <TaxPeriodBeginDt>2017-07-01</TaxPeriodBeginDt>
    <Filer>
      <EIN>562420913</EIN>
      <BusinessName>
        <BusinessNameLine1Txt>JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
      </BusinessName>
      <BusinessNameControlTxt>JEFF</BusinessNameControlTxt>
      <PhoneNum>4122676771</PhoneNum>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>565 COAL VALLEY ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>JEFFERSON HILLS</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>15025</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
    </Filer>
    <BusinessOfficerGrp>
      <PersonNm>CHARLES R MODISPACHER</PersonNm>
      <PersonTitleTxt>PRESIDENT &amp; CEO</PersonTitleTxt>
      <PhoneNum>4122676771</PhoneNum>
      <SignatureDt>2019-01-08</SignatureDt>
      <DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>1</DiscussWithPaidPreparerInd>
    </BusinessOfficerGrp>
    <PreparerPersonGrp>
      <PreparerPersonNm>JULIUS C GREEN CPA</PreparerPersonNm>
      <PTIN>P00350393</PTIN>
      <PhoneNum>2159720701</PhoneNum>
    </PreparerPersonGrp>
    <FilingSecurityInformation>
      <IPAddress>
        <IPv4AddressTxt>96.89.178.154</IPv4AddressTxt>
      </IPAddress>
      <IPDt>2019-01-08</IPDt>
      <IPTm>12:22:15</IPTm>
      <IPTimezoneCd>ES</IPTimezoneCd>
      <FilingLicenseTypeCd>P</FilingLicenseTypeCd>
      <AtSubmissionCreationDeviceId>DA39A3EE5E6B4B0D3255BFEF95601890AFD80709</AtSubmissionCreationDeviceId>
      <AtSubmissionFilingDeviceId>9D0D8DD59390B7764A3ECE0F40BBFE3618018605</AtSubmissionFilingDeviceId>
    </FilingSecurityInformation>
    <TaxYr>2017</TaxYr>
    <BuildTS>2019-02-21 02:37:17Z</BuildTS>
  </ReturnHeader>
  <ReturnData documentCnt="7">
    <IRS990 documentId="RetDoc1038000001" referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <PrincipalOfficerNm>CHARLES R MODISPACHER</PrincipalOfficerNm>
      <USAddress>
        <AddressLine1Txt>565 COAL VALLEY ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
        <CityNm>JEFFERSON HILLS</CityNm>
        <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
        <ZIPCd>15025</ZIPCd>
      </USAddress>
      <GrossReceiptsAmt>50550962</GrossReceiptsAmt>
      <GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>0</GroupReturnForAffiliatesInd>
      <Organization501c3Ind>X</Organization501c3Ind>
      <WebsiteAddressTxt>WWW.JEFFERSONRF.ORG</WebsiteAddressTxt>
      <TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>X</TypeOfOrganizationCorpInd>
      <FormationYr>2003</FormationYr>
      <LegalDomicileStateCd>PA</LegalDomicileStateCd>
      <ActivityOrMissionDesc>IMPROVE THE HEALTH &amp; WELL-BEING OF THE COMMUNITY OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL THROUGH GRANTMAKING, EDUCATION &amp; OUTREACH.</ActivityOrMissionDesc>
      <VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>20</VotingMembersGoverningBodyCnt>
      <VotingMembersIndependentCnt>19</VotingMembersIndependentCnt>
      <TotalEmployeeCnt>5</TotalEmployeeCnt>
      <TotalVolunteersCnt>19</TotalVolunteersCnt>
      <TotalGrossUBIAmt>0</TotalGrossUBIAmt>
      <NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>0</NetUnrelatedBusTxblIncmAmt>
      <PYContributionsGrantsAmt>0</PYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <CYContributionsGrantsAmt>0</CYContributionsGrantsAmt>
      <PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>0</PYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>0</CYProgramServiceRevenueAmt>
      <PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>3612818</PYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>4683729</CYInvestmentIncomeAmt>
      <PYOtherRevenueAmt>0</PYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <CYOtherRevenueAmt>0</CYOtherRevenueAmt>
      <PYTotalRevenueAmt>3612818</PYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <CYTotalRevenueAmt>4683729</CYTotalRevenueAmt>
      <PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>2007000</PYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>3019500</CYGrantsAndSimilarPaidAmt>
      <PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</PYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>0</CYBenefitsPaidToMembersAmt>
      <PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>402252</PYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>429361</CYSalariesCompEmpBnftPaidAmt>
      <PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</PYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>0</CYTotalProfFndrsngExpnsAmt>
      <CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>0</CYTotalFundraisingExpenseAmt>
      <PYOtherExpensesAmt>605161</PYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <CYOtherExpensesAmt>638636</CYOtherExpensesAmt>
      <PYTotalExpensesAmt>3014413</PYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <CYTotalExpensesAmt>4087497</CYTotalExpensesAmt>
      <PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>598405</PYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>596232</CYRevenuesLessExpensesAmt>
      <TotalAssetsBOYAmt>93132112</TotalAssetsBOYAmt>
      <TotalAssetsEOYAmt>98795344</TotalAssetsEOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>650931</TotalLiabilitiesBOYAmt>
      <TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>1468283</TotalLiabilitiesEOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>92481181</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesBOYAmt>
      <NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>97327061</NetAssetsOrFundBalancesEOYAmt>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartIIIInd>
      <MissionDesc>THE MISSION OF THE JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION IS TO IMPROVE THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF THE COMMUNITY OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL THROUGH GRANTMAKING, EDUCATION AND OUTREACH. THE FOUNDATION WILL SERVE THE COMMUNITY WITH INTEGRITY AND TRANSPARENCY. ITS MAJOR PRIORITIES INCLUDE: INCREASING HEALTH ACCESS AND PREVENTION, IMPROVING CHILD AND FAMILY OUTCOMES AND STRENGTHENING VULNERABLE POPULATIONS AND COMMUNITIES.</MissionDesc>
      <SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>0</SignificantNewProgramSrvcInd>
      <SignificantChangeInd>0</SignificantChangeInd>
      <ExpenseAmt>1352500</ExpenseAmt>
      <GrantAmt>1352500</GrantAmt>
      <RevenueAmt>0</RevenueAmt>
      <Desc>THE JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION AWARDED 33 NEW GRANTS TOTALING $3,019,500 TO ORGANIZATIONS WHICH SUPPORT OUR MISSION TO FOCUS ON HEALTH AND WELLNESS IN THE JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AREA (SOUTH HILLS AND LOWER MON VALLEY) IN ITS RECENT YEAR ENDING JUNE 30, 2018. GRANTS WERE AWARDED DURING THREE GRANT CYCLES IN EACH OF THREE PRIORITY AREAS: INCREASING HEALTH ACCESS AND PREVENTION, IMPROVING CHILD AND FAMILY OUTCOMES AND STRENGTHENING POPULATIONS AND COMMUNITIES. SEVERAL GRANTS THIS YEAR PROMOTED INNOVATIONS IN ENSURING ACCESS TO BASIC NUTRITION AND HEALTHY FOOD WHICH IS ESSENTIAL FOR GOOD HEALTH. 412 FOOD RESCUE WAS AWARDED A TWO-YEAR $50,000 GRANT FOR RECOVERING AND REDISTRIBUTING FOOD TO LOCAL COMMUNITY PARTNERS, OFFERING COMMUNITY-BASED FOOD EDUCATION AND PILOTING HEALTHY PREPARED MEALS IN CORNER STORES. GREATER PITTSBURGH FOOD BANK RECEIVED TWO GRANTS, THE FIRST FOR A $10,000 BACKPACK FOOD DISTRIBUTION PROGRAM WITH A LOCAL HIGH SCHOOL AND A $68,000 GRANT TO PILOT MEDICALLY TAILORED FOOD BOXES FOR FOOD INSECURE PATIENTS AT JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AND WITH SQUIRREL HILL HEALTH CENTER. TWO GRANTS FOCUSED ON HEALTH IN THE MON VALLEY AREA; STEEL RIVERS COUNCIL OF GOVERNMENTS HAS A $40,000 AWARD TO PARTNER WITH THE ALLEGHENY COUNTY HEALTH DEPARTMENT FOR DATA ANALYSIS AND COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT TO UNDERSTAND HEALTH ACCESS ISSUES IN THE AREA, WHILE DUQUESNE UNIVERSITY'S $75,000 GRANT IS DESIGNED TO INCREASE THE CAPACITY AND SUSTAINABILITY OF A SCHOOL-BASED ASTHMA CLINIC IN THE CITY OF CLAIRTON. THE FOUNDATION CONTINUES ITS SUPPORT OF OPIOID OVERDOSE EFFORTS IN SUPPORTING THE GLASSPORT DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION WITH $8500 TO FUND MARKETING OF ITS SUBSTANCE ABUSE REALITY TOUR AND $10,000 TO SALTWORKS TO PRODUCE ITS LIVE THEATER PRODUCTIONS FOCUSED ON THE OPIOID EPIDEMIC TO LOCAL MIDDLE AND HIGH SCHOOLS. TWO GRANTS SUPPORT ESSENTIAL HEALTH SUPPLIES AND EQUIPMENT; THE PLEASANT HILLS POLICE DEPARTMENT ($41,000) PARTNERED WITH TWO OTHER BOROUGHS TO PLACE DEFIBRILLATORS IN POLICE PATROL VEHICLES, WHILE A GRANT OF $50,000 TO GLOBAL LINKS PLACES SURPLUS MEDICAL SUPPLIES WITH VULNERABLE RESIDENTS THROUGH A PARTNERSHIP WITH THREE LOCAL HUMAN SERVICE AGENCIES. THE FOUNDATION AWARDED ITS LARGEST GRANT TO DATE ($1,000,000 OVER 4 YEARS) TO JEFFERSON HOSPITAL OF THE ALLEGHENY HEALTH NETWORK FOR THE FRONT DOOR INITIATIVE TO CREATE A MODEL OF EXCELLENCE IN EMERGENCY SERVICES BY BUILDING THE CAPACITY TO ADDRESS THE SOCIAL DETERMINANTS OF HEALTH AS AN EXPANDED FACILITY IS CONSTRUCTED. A PLAN WILL BE DEVELOPED TO INCLUDE INNOVATIONS SUCH AS ENHANCED STAFF CAPACITIES, STRONG REFERRAL RELATIONSHIPS, IMPROVED PATIENT AND SYSTEM OUTCOMES AND ENRICHED COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.</Desc>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActy2Grp>
        <ExpenseAmt>500000</ExpenseAmt>
        <GrantAmt>500000</GrantAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>0</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>THE FOUNDATION HAS FOCUSED GRANTMAKING ON MATERNAL AND INFANT NEEDS AND SUPPORTS CRIB FOR KIDS WITH A $45,000 GRANT TO EXTEND ITS SAFE SLEEP OUTREACH AND INTERVENTION TO FIRST RESPONDERS WITH INFORMATION AND THE DISTRIBUTION OF PORTABLE CRIBS TO REDUCE INFANT DEATHS. AFTERSCHOOL AND SUMMER PROGRAMS CAN PROVIDE IMPORTANT POSITIVE ALTERNATIVE ACTIVITIES, SKILLS AND EDUCATION FOR YOUTH. USING ITS CENTERS IN MCKEESPORT AND DUQUESNE, THE BOYS &amp; GIRLS CLUB OF WESTERN PA ($50,000) WILL CONTINUE TO DEVELOP ITS SUCCESSFUL NEW PROGRAM TO SERVE 225 TEENS. MUSA (METHODIST UNION OF SOCIAL AGENCIES FOR $40,000) PROVIDES YEAR-ROUND OUT-OF-SCHOOL TIME PROGRAMS FOR 130 LOW-INCOME YOUTH AND FAMILIES FROM HOMESTEAD, WEST HOMESTEAD AND MUNHALL AND NEARBY COMMUNITIES. SISTERS PLACE HAS A TWO-YEAR GRANT FOR $125,000 TO BUILD STABILITY FOR HOMELESS FAMILIES LED BY SINGLE PARENTS AND A STRATEGIC PLANNING PROCESS TO BUILD ITS OWN ORGANIZATIONAL CAPACITY. SEVERAL GRANTS PROMOTE CHILD AND FAMILY WELLNESS OUTCOMES THROUGH THE USE OF POSITIVE SHARED EXPERIENCES AND CREATIVE TOOLS SUCH AS THE ARTS AND OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES. WQED IS HOSTING CREATIVE WORKSHOPS AT THREE LIBRARY &amp; COMMUNITY SITES TO PROMOTE POSITIVE CONNECTIONS TO LEARNING AND FAMILY ENGAGEMENT WITH A GRANT OF $50,000. BEVERLY'S BIRTHDAYS HAS A GRANT OF $20,000 TO CREATE POSITIVE EXPERIENCES FOR YOUNG, LOW-INCOME CHILDREN AND THEIR FAMILIES BY PROVIDING BIRTHDAY CHEER PROGRAMS ONSITE AT LOCAL SHELTERS AND COMMUNITY SITES. WITH A GRANT OF $90,000 OVER TWO YEARS, THE CENTER OF LIFE IS INFUSING ITS EXPERTISE USING THE ARTS WITH YOUTH AND FAMILIES TO BUILD TEAMWORK, PROBLEM-SOLVING, AND SELF-ESTEEM AND ENHANCE ITS YOUTH PARTNER PROGRAMS. THE STUDENT CONVERSATION ASSOCIATION ($40,000) PARTNERS WITH MELTING POT MINISTRIES TO PROVIDE PAID SUMMER EMPLOYMENT THROUGH CONSERVATION WORK IN SOUTH PARK WHILE INCREASING PHYSICAL ACTIVITY, ENVIRONMENTAL KNOWLEDGE, AND JOB SKILLS. VENTURE OUTDOORS ($40,000) PARTNERS WITH LOCAL PROGRAMS TO PROMOTE HEALTHY LIFESTYLES AND IS BUILDING ON ITS ENGAGING YOUTH ACTIVITIES WHILE ADDING TARGETED PROGRAMMING FOR FAMILIES AND OLDER ADULTS.</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActy2Grp>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActy3Grp>
        <ExpenseAmt>1167000</ExpenseAmt>
        <GrantAmt>1167000</GrantAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>0</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>SEVERAL FOUNDATION GRANTS SUPPORT KEY ORGANIZATIONS WHICH ARE RESOURCES FOR THE BROADER COMMUNITY. THE ALLEGHENY COUNTY LIBRARY ASSOCIATION WAS AWARDED A TWO-YEAR GRANT FOR $100,000 TO EXPAND THE CAPACITY OF TEN LOCAL LIBRARIES AS COMMUNITY RESOURCE SITES WITH NEW PARTNERSHIPS AND PROGRAMMING. ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT SOUTH HAS GRANT SUPPORT OF $250,000 OVER TWO YEARS TO OFFER COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT EXPERTISE, TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE AND PROJECT MANAGEMENT FOR ORGANIZATIONS AND COMMUNITIES WHICH ADVANCES AND ALIGNS WITH FOUNDATION AND COLLABORATIVE PRIORITIES. ANOTHER DEVELOPING RESOURCE FOR THE MON VALLEY AREA IS A COMMUNITY CENTER HOSTED BY PENN STATE GREATER ALLEGHENY ($40,000) IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE CITY OF MCKEESPORT TO ADDRESS JOBLESSNESS AND FOOD INSECURITY.ANOTHER SET OF GRANT AWARDS IN THIS CATEGORY ARE DESIGNED TO ENHANCE RESIDENT ACCESS TO AND SKILL-BUILDING FOR GREATER OPPORTUNITIES IN COMMUNITY PARTICIPATION. GREATER PITTSBURGH LITERACY COUNCIL (NOW KNOWN AS LITERACY PITTSBURGH) WAS AWARDED $60,000 TO MEET THE INCREASING DEMAND FOR LITERACY TRAINING IN THE AREA, WHILE NEIGHBORWORKS WESTERN PA HAS A $30,000 GRANT AWARD AND IS OFFERING FINANCIAL EDUCATION WORKSHOPS AND COACHING TO BUILD FINANCIAL LITERACY. THE CENTER FOR HEARING, IN PARTNERSHIP WITH GLOBAL WORDSMITHS, WILL INCREASE THE LANGUAGE ACCESS CAPACITY OF 12-15 COLLABORATIVE ORGANIZATIONS SERVING IMMIGRANT AND INTERNATIONAL POPULATIONS THROUGH INTEGRATION OF LANGUAGE ACCESS PLANS, TRAINING AND TRANSLATION OF DOCUMENTS WITH A TWO YEAR GRANT AWARD OF $120,000. THE FOUNDATION HAS A STRONG INTEREST AND COMMITMENT TO BUILD THE CAPACITY OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS FOR LOCAL IMPACT, AS WELL AS STRENGTHENING LOCAL LEADERSHIP. A GRANT TO THE FORBES FUNDS ($40,000) BUILDS CAPACITY THROUGH INDIVIDUAL EXECUTIVE COACHING AND THE CREATION OF SEVERAL PEER LEARNING COHORTS DESIGNED FOR NONPROFIT EXECUTIVES, EMERGING LEADERS AND THE USE OF DATA MAPPING AND ANALYTICS. IN OUR BACKYARDS INC (IOBY) OFFERS A TRAINING IN CROWDFUNDING WITH MATCH FUNDS AND COACHING TO DEVELOP THE CAPACITY AND SUSTAINABILITY OF SMALL, VOLUNTEER-LED ORGANIZATIONS IN THE AREA WITH A $60,000 GRANT. TWO GRANTS WERE DESIGNED TO STRENGTHEN THE HUMAN SERVICES FABRIC FOR THE CITY OF CLAIRTON AND ITS AREA. A GRANT IN THE AMOUNT OF $35,000 TO GWEN'S GIRLS SUPPORTS OPTIONS FOR YOUTH AND FAMILY ENGAGEMENT THROUGH A STRATEGIC PROCESS TO EXPLORE AN AFFILIATION WITH ANOTHER LOCAL GROUP. A $110,000 GRANT AWARD FOR TWO YEARS TO ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT SOUTH SUPPORTS THE COORDINATION AND EXPANSION OF HUMAN SERVICE AND HEALTH RESOURCES IN THE CLAIRTON AREA THROUGH ENHANCING THE CAPACITY OF NEW ORGANIZATION CLAIRTON CARES. A MINI-GRANT OF $2000 TO GWEN'S GIRLS SUPPORTS BIMONTHLY TOPICAL MEETINGS OF A PEER-LED COLLABORATIVE ACTION TEAM CALLED EAT N EDUCATE. GRANT SUPPORT IS ALSO TARGETED TO VULNERABLE POPULATIONS TO BUILD ON THEIR STRENGTHS AND RESILIENCY. EASTERN AREA ADULT SERVICES IS USING A $50,000 GRANT AWARD TO IMPROVE ITS CAPACITY TO SERVE VULNERABLE OLDER ADULTS IN HOME CARE OR IN NEED OF PROTECTIVE SERVICES BY EXPLORING NEW MODELS OF SERVICE DELIVERY. A GRANT AWARD TO THE MISSION CONTINUES OF $100,000 OVER TWO YEARS ENGAGES POST-911 VETERANS AS COMMUNITY VOLUNTEERS IN A JEFFERSON SERVICE PLATOON SUPPORTING THE REFUGEE AND IMMIGRANT POPULATION IN PARTNERSHIP WITH LOCAL ORGANIZATIONS. ANOTHER PROGRAM BUILT ON LEVERAGING VOLUNTEER SERVICES IN THE COMMUNITY IS LED BY UNITED WAY OF SOUTHWESTERN PA WITH TARGETED SERVICES TO OLDER ADULTS AGING IN PLACE IN THE COMMUNITY AND MIDDLE SCHOOL YOUTH THROUGH A GRANT AWARD OF $70,000.</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActy3Grp>
      <ProgSrvcAccomActyOtherGrp>
        <ExpenseAmt>522559</ExpenseAmt>
        <GrantAmt>0</GrantAmt>
        <RevenueAmt>0</RevenueAmt>
        <Desc>THE JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION AWARDED 33 NEW GRANTS TOTALING $3,019,500 TO ORGANIZATIONS WHICH SUPPORT OUR MISSION TO FOCUS ON HEALTH AND WELLNESS IN THE JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AREA (SOUTH HILLS AND LOWER MON VALLEY) IN ITS RECENT YEAR ENDING JUNE 30, 2018. GRANTS WERE AWARDED DURING THREE GRANT CYCLES IN EACH OF THREE PRIORITY AREAS: INCREASING HEALTH ACCESS AND PREVENTION, IMPROVING CHILD AND FAMILY OUTCOMES AND STRENGTHENING POPULATIONS AND COMMUNITIES. STRATEGIC PLANNING &amp; PRIORITIES THE JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION IS COMMITTED TO OPERATE AS A LEARNING ORGANIZATION, AND WE CONTINUALLY SEEK TO UNDERSTAND CHANGING AND EMERGING NEEDS IN OUR AREA. OUR WORK IS GUIDED BY COMMUNITY HEALTH ASSESSMENTS (ALLEGHENY HEALTH NETWORK, JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AND THE ALLEGHENY COUNTY HEALTH DEPARTMENT), THE KNOWLEDGE AND INSIGHTS OF OUR GRANTEES, THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE, LOCAL LEADERS AND REGULAR MEETINGS WITH HOSPITAL LEADERSHIP. IN ADDITION, THE BOARD ENGAGES IN ONGOING DEVELOPMENT WITH SPEAKERS ON TOPICS AS VARIED AS ADVOCACY, SOCIAL DETERMINANTS OF HEALTH, GRANT IMPACTS AND UNIVERSITY RESEARCH. IN THE FALL OF 2018, THE FOUNDATION WILL INSTITUTE A NEW COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT INITIATIVE, CALLED AROUND THE TABLE SOUTH, DESIGNED TO ENGAGE 1000 LOCAL RESIDENTS AND CAPTURE COMMUNITY CONCERNS, PRIORITIES AND IDEAS.THE FOUNDATION'S GRANTS COMMITTEE LAUNCHED ITS NEW FUNDING YEAR WITH A DAYLONG RETREAT IN THE SUMMER OF 2017 WITH ROBUST DISCUSSION BASED ON A REVIEW OF GRANTMAKING DATA AND COMMUNITY TRENDS. THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE, AN 85-MEMBER NETWORK OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS HOSTED BY THE FOUNDATION, ALSO HOSTED A RETREAT WITH TWO DOZEN LEADERS. AS A RESULT, BOTH THE FOUNDATION AND THE COLLABORATIVE HAVE ADDED A NEW FOCUS ON WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT AND A RENEWED FOCUS ON BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, PARTICULARLY THE IMPACT OF THE OPIOID OVERDOSE EPIDEMIC. DURING THE PAST YEAR, A LOCAL WORKFORCE ASSESSMENT WAS CONDUCTED THROUGH A GRANT AND IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE COLLABORATIVE AND THE RESULTS ARE HELPING THE GUIDE A WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT INITIATIVE. A MULTI-YEAR GRANT TO THE LOCAL NEEDLE EXCHANGE PROGRAM, PREVENTION POINT, FOR HARM REDUCTION, PEER SPECIALISTS AND A PUBLIC CAMPAIGN IS HELPING TO FOCUS LOCAL EFFORTS RELATED TO ADDRESSING THE OPIOID OVERDOSE EPIDEMIC.OPERATIONAL CHANGES IN THE SPRING OF 2018, THE FOUNDATION ADDED A NEW STAFF FULLTIME PROGRAM ASSOCIATE ROLE TO SUPPORT THE WORK OF THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE AS WELL AS THE OTHER EXTENSIVE CONVENING ACTIVITIES OF THE FOUNDATION SUCH AS ITS ANNUAL FORUM AND OTHER GROUPS. THE FOUNDATION ADOPTED NEW FORMATS IN PRESENTATION OF COMMITTEE MATERIALS INCLUDING THE USE OF DASHBOARDS.4TH ANNUAL JEFFERSON FORUM: TELLING OUR STORY IN MAY 2018, THE FOUNDATION HOSTED ANOTHER HIGHLY SUCCESSFUL DAYLONG CONFERENCE ATTRACTING 138 ORGANIZATIONS FOCUSED ON THE JEFFERSON AREA WITH A CAPACITY CROWD OF 245 PARTICIPANTS (100% HIGHLY SATISFIED AND LIKELY TO ATTEND AGAIN). FEATURED SPEAKER STEPHEN SMITH WAS FOLLOWED BY A PANEL OF LOCAL LEADERS WHO SHARED THEIR PERSONAL STORIES. THE LOBBY CONTAINED A FORUM PHOTO BOOTH TO COLLECT THE STORIES AND PASSIONS OF PARTICIPANTS AND A PHOTO EXHIBIT OF TEEN IMMIGRANTS CALLED TWO CULTURES ONE ME. SALTWORKS PERFORMED A CONDENSED VERSION OF THEIR NEW PLAY ABOUT OPIOID OVERDOSE. SIX WORKSHOPS WERE OFFERED ON MINDFULNESS, ADDICTION, GRASSROOTS ADVOCACY, LANGUAGE ACCESS, MOTIVATIONAL INTERVIEWING, AND SUSTAINABLE ORGANIZATIONS. ALL PARTICIPANTS RECEIVED A COPY OF THE NEW 3RD EDITION OF THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY DIRECTORY. THE DAY CONCLUDED WITH THE JEFFERSON CAFE WHICH INCLUDED 20 DIFFERENT FACILITATED ROUNDTABLE DISCUSSIONS ON TOPICS SUGGESTED BY THE VISION COUNCIL AND PARTICIPANTS. THEMES THAT EMERGED INCLUDED: ADVOCACY, STIGMA AND INCLUSION.</Desc>
      </ProgSrvcAccomActyOtherGrp>
      <TotalOtherProgSrvcExpenseAmt>522559</TotalOtherProgSrvcExpenseAmt>
      <TotalOtherProgSrvcGrantAmt>0</TotalOtherProgSrvcGrantAmt>
      <TotalOtherProgSrvcRevenueAmt>0</TotalOtherProgSrvcRevenueAmt>
      <TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>3542059</TotalProgramServiceExpensesAmt>
      <DescribedInSection501c3Ind referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1039100001">1</DescribedInSection501c3Ind>
      <ScheduleBRequiredInd>0</ScheduleBRequiredInd>
      <PoliticalCampaignActyInd>0</PoliticalCampaignActyInd>
      <LobbyingActivitiesInd>0</LobbyingActivitiesInd>
      <SubjectToProxyTaxInd>0</SubjectToProxyTaxInd>
      <DonorAdvisedFundInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</DonorAdvisedFundInd>
      <ConservationEasementsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConservationEasementsInd>
      <CollectionsOfArtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CollectionsOfArtInd>
      <CreditCounselingInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</CreditCounselingInd>
      <TempOrPermanentEndowmentsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</TempOrPermanentEndowmentsInd>
      <ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</ReportLandBuildingEquipmentInd>
      <ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportInvestmentsOtherSecInd>
      <ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportProgramRelatedInvstInd>
      <ReportOtherAssetsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportOtherAssetsInd>
      <ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ReportOtherLiabilitiesInd>
      <IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</IncludeFIN48FootnoteInd>
      <IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">1</IndependentAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1040000001">0</ConsolidatedAuditFinclStmtInd>
      <SchoolOperatingInd>0</SchoolOperatingInd>
      <ForeignOfficeInd>0</ForeignOfficeInd>
      <ForeignActivitiesInd>0</ForeignActivitiesInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToOrgInd>0</MoreThan5000KToOrgInd>
      <MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd>0</MoreThan5000KToIndividualsInd>
      <ProfessionalFundraisingInd>0</ProfessionalFundraisingInd>
      <FundraisingActivitiesInd>0</FundraisingActivitiesInd>
      <GamingActivitiesInd>0</GamingActivitiesInd>
      <OperateHospitalInd>0</OperateHospitalInd>
      <GrantsToOrganizationsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041900001">1</GrantsToOrganizationsInd>
      <GrantsToIndividualsInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1041900001">0</GrantsToIndividualsInd>
      <ScheduleJRequiredInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1042400001">1</ScheduleJRequiredInd>
      <TaxExemptBondsInd>0</TaxExemptBondsInd>
      <EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>0</EngagedInExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <PYExcessBenefitTransInd>0</PYExcessBenefitTransInd>
      <LoanOutstandingInd>0</LoanOutstandingInd>
      <GrantToRelatedPersonInd>0</GrantToRelatedPersonInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd>0</BusinessRlnWithOrgMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd>0</BusinessRlnWithFamMemInd>
      <BusinessRlnWithOfficerEntInd>0</BusinessRlnWithOfficerEntInd>
      <DeductibleNonCashContriInd>0</DeductibleNonCashContriInd>
      <DeductibleArtContributionInd>0</DeductibleArtContributionInd>
      <TerminateOperationsInd>0</TerminateOperationsInd>
      <PartialLiquidationInd>0</PartialLiquidationInd>
      <DisregardedEntityInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</DisregardedEntityInd>
      <RelatedEntityInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">1</RelatedEntityInd>
      <RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>0</RelatedOrganizationCtrlEntInd>
      <TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</TrnsfrExmptNonChrtblRltdOrgInd>
      <ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd referenceDocumentId="RetDoc1043400001">0</ActivitiesConductedPrtshpInd>
      <ScheduleORequiredInd>1</ScheduleORequiredInd>
      <IRPDocumentCnt>5</IRPDocumentCnt>
      <IRPDocumentW2GCnt>0</IRPDocumentW2GCnt>
      <BackupWthldComplianceInd>1</BackupWthldComplianceInd>
      <EmployeeCnt>5</EmployeeCnt>
      <EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>1</EmploymentTaxReturnsFiledInd>
      <UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>0</UnrelatedBusIncmOverLimitInd>
      <ForeignFinancialAccountInd>0</ForeignFinancialAccountInd>
      <ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>0</ProhibitedTaxShelterTransInd>
      <TaxablePartyNotificationInd>0</TaxablePartyNotificationInd>
      <NondeductibleContributionsInd>0</NondeductibleContributionsInd>
      <QuidProQuoContributionsInd>0</QuidProQuoContributionsInd>
      <Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>0</Form8282PropertyDisposedOfInd>
      <RcvFndsToPayPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>0</RcvFndsToPayPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>
      <PayPremiumsPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>0</PayPremiumsPrsnlBnftCntrctInd>
      <IndoorTanningServicesInd>0</IndoorTanningServicesInd>
      <InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>X</InfoInScheduleOPartVIInd>
      <GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>20</GoverningBodyVotingMembersCnt>
      <IndependentVotingMemberCnt>19</IndependentVotingMemberCnt>
      <FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>1</FamilyOrBusinessRlnInd>
      <DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>0</DelegationOfMgmtDutiesInd>
      <ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>0</ChangeToOrgDocumentsInd>
      <MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>0</MaterialDiversionOrMisuseInd>
      <MembersOrStockholdersInd>0</MembersOrStockholdersInd>
      <ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>0</ElectionOfBoardMembersInd>
      <DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>0</DecisionsSubjectToApprovaInd>
      <MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>1</MinutesOfGoverningBodyInd>
      <MinutesOfCommitteesInd>1</MinutesOfCommitteesInd>
      <OfficerMailingAddressInd>0</OfficerMailingAddressInd>
      <LocalChaptersInd>0</LocalChaptersInd>
      <Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>1</Form990ProvidedToGvrnBodyInd>
      <ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>1</ConflictOfInterestPolicyInd>
      <AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>1</AnnualDisclosureCoveredPrsnInd>
      <RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>1</RegularMonitoringEnfrcInd>
      <WhistleblowerPolicyInd>1</WhistleblowerPolicyInd>
      <DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>1</DocumentRetentionPolicyInd>
      <CompensationProcessCEOInd>1</CompensationProcessCEOInd>
      <CompensationProcessOtherInd>1</CompensationProcessOtherInd>
      <InvestmentInJointVentureInd>0</InvestmentInJointVentureInd>
      <StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>PA</StatesWhereCopyOfReturnIsFldCd>
      <OwnWebsiteInd>X</OwnWebsiteInd>
      <UponRequestInd>X</UponRequestInd>
      <BooksInCareOfDetail>
        <BusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>CHARLES R MODISPACHER PRESIDENT &amp; CEO</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </BusinessName>
        <PhoneNum>4122676766</PhoneNum>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>565 COAL VALLEY ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>JEFFERSON HILLS</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15025</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
      </BooksInCareOfDetail>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>JAMES G GRAHAM</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>CHAIRPERSON</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>RICHARD W TALARICO</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>FIRST VICE CHAIRMAN</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>JOHN R ECHEMENT</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>2ND VICE CHAIR; PAST PRES</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>GARY W DESCHAMPS</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>J WILLIAM RICHARDSON</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>TREASURER</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>EDWARD R MARASCO</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>SECRETARY</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>CHARLES R MODISPACHER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>PRESIDENT &amp; CEO</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>20.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>50000</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>AARON B BILLGER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>RICHARD F COLLINS MD</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>JOHN J DEMPSTER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>GREGORY M DEVINE</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>GARY L EVANS</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>FINANCE COMMITTEE CHAIR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>2.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>KAREN A EVANS</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>EVAN S FRAZIER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>MARK P GANNON MD</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>GREGORY A HARBAUGH</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>KEVIN D LANGHOLZ</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>DANIEL A ONORATO</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>HARRY J SICHI</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>MATTHEW P VIRGIN</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>DIRECTOR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>1.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>X</IndividualTrusteeOrDirectorInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>0</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
        <PersonNm>MARY PHAN-GRUBER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR/ASST TR</TitleTxt>
        <AverageHoursPerWeekRt>40.00</AverageHoursPerWeekRt>
        <OfficerInd>X</OfficerInd>
        <ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>147000</ReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
        <ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>0</ReportableCompFromRltdOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationAmt>22262</OtherCompensationAmt>
      </Form990PartVIISectionAGrp>
      <TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>197000</TotalReportableCompFromOrgAmt>
      <TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>0</TotReportableCompRltdOrgAmt>
      <TotalOtherCompensationAmt>22262</TotalOtherCompensationAmt>
      <IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>1</IndivRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>0</FormerOfcrEmployeesListedInd>
      <TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>1</TotalCompGreaterThan150KInd>
      <CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>0</CompensationFromOtherSrcsInd>
      <CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>0</CntrctRcvdGreaterThan100KCnt>
      <InvestmentIncomeGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>1603844</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>1603844</ExclusionAmt>
      </InvestmentIncomeGrp>
      <GrossAmountSalesAssetsGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>48947118</SecuritiesAmt>
      </GrossAmountSalesAssetsGrp>
      <LessCostOthBasisSalesExpnssGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>45867233</SecuritiesAmt>
      </LessCostOthBasisSalesExpnssGrp>
      <GainOrLossGrp>
        <SecuritiesAmt>3079885</SecuritiesAmt>
      </GainOrLossGrp>
      <NetGainOrLossInvestmentsGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>3079885</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>3079885</ExclusionAmt>
      </NetGainOrLossInvestmentsGrp>
      <TotalRevenueGrp>
        <TotalRevenueColumnAmt>4683729</TotalRevenueColumnAmt>
        <RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>0</RelatedOrExemptFuncIncomeAmt>
        <UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>0</UnrelatedBusinessRevenueAmt>
        <ExclusionAmt>4683729</ExclusionAmt>
      </TotalRevenueGrp>
      <GrantsToDomesticOrgsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>3019500</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>3019500</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </GrantsToDomesticOrgsGrp>
      <CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>207955</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>137485</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>70470</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </CompCurrentOfcrDirectorsGrp>
      <OtherSalariesAndWagesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>155987</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>133070</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>22917</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherSalariesAndWagesGrp>
      <PensionPlanContributionsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>5783</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>4207</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1576</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </PensionPlanContributionsGrp>
      <OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>33478</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>24742</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>8736</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherEmployeeBenefitsGrp>
      <PayrollTaxesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>26158</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>19332</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>6826</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </PayrollTaxesGrp>
      <FeesForServicesLegalGrp>
        <TotalAmt>12041</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>12041</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesLegalGrp>
      <FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
        <TotalAmt>24050</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>24050</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesAccountingGrp>
      <FeesForSrvcInvstMgmntFeesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>340800</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>340800</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForSrvcInvstMgmntFeesGrp>
      <FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
        <TotalAmt>43433</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>39762</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>3671</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </FeesForServicesOtherGrp>
      <OfficeExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>10432</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>7511</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>2921</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OfficeExpensesGrp>
      <InformationTechnologyGrp>
        <TotalAmt>29079</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>20937</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>8142</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </InformationTechnologyGrp>
      <OccupancyGrp>
        <TotalAmt>22426</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>16147</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>6279</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OccupancyGrp>
      <TravelGrp>
        <TotalAmt>1339</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>964</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>375</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </TravelGrp>
      <ConferencesMeetingsGrp>
        <TotalAmt>12893</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>9283</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>3610</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </ConferencesMeetingsGrp>
      <DepreciationDepletionGrp>
        <TotalAmt>21809</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>21809</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </DepreciationDepletionGrp>
      <InsuranceGrp>
        <TotalAmt>6122</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>4408</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1714</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </InsuranceGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>PROGRAM INITIATIVES</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>82646</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>82646</ProgramServicesAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>DUES &amp; MEMBERSHIPS</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>16462</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>11852</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>4610</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>PROGRAM &amp; STAFF DEVEL.</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>9000</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>6480</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>2520</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <OtherExpensesGrp>
        <Desc>REPAIRS &amp; MAINTENANCE</Desc>
        <TotalAmt>5186</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>3733</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>1453</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </OtherExpensesGrp>
      <AllOtherExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>918</TotalAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>918</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
      </AllOtherExpensesGrp>
      <TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
        <TotalAmt>4087497</TotalAmt>
        <ProgramServicesAmt>3542059</ProgramServicesAmt>
        <ManagementAndGeneralAmt>545438</ManagementAndGeneralAmt>
        <FundraisingAmt>0</FundraisingAmt>
      </TotalFunctionalExpensesGrp>
      <SavingsAndTempCashInvstGrp>
        <BOYAmt>279624</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>128616</EOYAmt>
      </SavingsAndTempCashInvstGrp>
      <PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>11158</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>11179</EOYAmt>
      </PrepaidExpensesDefrdChargesGrp>
      <LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>106060</LandBldgEquipCostOrOtherBssAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>48623</LandBldgEquipAccumDeprecAmt>
      <LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
        <BOYAmt>77411</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>57437</EOYAmt>
      </LandBldgEquipBasisNetGrp>
      <InvestmentsPubTradedSecGrp>
        <BOYAmt>90219416</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>95542978</EOYAmt>
      </InvestmentsPubTradedSecGrp>
      <InvestmentsOtherSecuritiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>2544503</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>3055134</EOYAmt>
      </InvestmentsOtherSecuritiesGrp>
      <TotalAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>93132112</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>98795344</EOYAmt>
      </TotalAssetsGrp>
      <AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
        <BOYAmt>71931</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>85283</EOYAmt>
      </AccountsPayableAccrExpnssGrp>
      <GrantsPayableGrp>
        <BOYAmt>579000</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>1383000</EOYAmt>
      </GrantsPayableGrp>
      <TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
        <BOYAmt>650931</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>1468283</EOYAmt>
      </TotalLiabilitiesGrp>
      <OrganizationFollowsSFAS117Ind>X</OrganizationFollowsSFAS117Ind>
      <UnrestrictedNetAssetsGrp>
        <BOYAmt>92481181</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>97327061</EOYAmt>
      </UnrestrictedNetAssetsGrp>
      <TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>92481181</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>97327061</EOYAmt>
      </TotalNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
        <BOYAmt>93132112</BOYAmt>
        <EOYAmt>98795344</EOYAmt>
      </TotLiabNetAssetsFundBalanceGrp>
      <ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>596232</ReconcilationRevenueExpnssAmt>
      <NetUnrlzdGainsLossesInvstAmt>4249648</NetUnrlzdGainsLossesInvstAmt>
      <OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>0</OtherChangesInNetAssetsAmt>
      <MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>X</MethodOfAccountingAccrualInd>
      <AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>0</AccountantCompileOrReviewInd>
      <FSAuditedInd>1</FSAuditedInd>
      <FSAuditedBasisGrp>
        <SeparateBasisFinclStmtInd>X</SeparateBasisFinclStmtInd>
      </FSAuditedBasisGrp>
      <AuditCommitteeInd>1</AuditCommitteeInd>
      <FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>0</FederalGrantAuditRequiredInd>
    </IRS990>
    <IRS990ScheduleA documentId="RetDoc1039100001">
      <SupportingOrganization509a3Ind>X</SupportingOrganization509a3Ind>
      <SupportingOrgType3FuncIntInd>X</SupportingOrgType3FuncIntInd>
      <SupportedOrganizationsCnt>1</SupportedOrganizationsCnt>
      <SupportedOrgInformationGrp>
        <SupportedOrganizationName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>JEFFERSON HOSPITAL</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </SupportedOrganizationName>
        <EIN>251260215</EIN>
        <OrganizationTypeCd>3</OrganizationTypeCd>
        <GoverningDocumentListedInd>1</GoverningDocumentListedInd>
        <SupportAmt>1000000</SupportAmt>
        <OtherSupportAmt>0</OtherSupportAmt>
      </SupportedOrgInformationGrp>
      <SupportedOrganizationsTotalCnt>1</SupportedOrganizationsTotalCnt>
      <SupportSumAmt>1000000</SupportSumAmt>
      <OtherSupportSumAmt>0</OtherSupportSumAmt>
      <Form990SchASupportingOrgGrp>
        <ListedByNameGoverningDocInd>1</ListedByNameGoverningDocInd>
        <SuprtOrgNoIRSDeterminationInd>0</SuprtOrgNoIRSDeterminationInd>
        <SupportedOrgSectionC456Ind>0</SupportedOrgSectionC456Ind>
        <SupportedOrgNotOrganizedUSInd>0</SupportedOrgNotOrganizedUSInd>
        <OrganizationChangeSuprtOrgInd>0</OrganizationChangeSuprtOrgInd>
        <SupportNonSupportedOrgInd>0</SupportNonSupportedOrgInd>
        <PaymentSubstantialContribtrInd>0</PaymentSubstantialContribtrInd>
        <LoanDisqualifiedPersonInd>0</LoanDisqualifiedPersonInd>
        <ControlledDisqualifiedPrsnInd>0</ControlledDisqualifiedPrsnInd>
        <DisqualifiedPrsnControllIntInd>0</DisqualifiedPrsnControllIntInd>
        <DisqualifiedPrsnOwnrIntInd>0</DisqualifiedPrsnOwnrIntInd>
        <ExcessBusinessHoldingsRulesInd>0</ExcessBusinessHoldingsRulesInd>
        <ContributionControllerInd>0</ContributionControllerInd>
        <ContributionFamilyInd>0</ContributionFamilyInd>
        <Contribution35ControlledInd>0</Contribution35ControlledInd>
      </Form990SchASupportingOrgGrp>
      <Form990SchAType3SprtOrgAllGrp>
        <TimelyProvidedDocumentsInd>1</TimelyProvidedDocumentsInd>
        <OfficersCloseRelationshipInd>1</OfficersCloseRelationshipInd>
        <SupportedOrgVoiceInvestmentInd>1</SupportedOrgVoiceInvestmentInd>
      </Form990SchAType3SprtOrgAllGrp>
      <Form990SchAType3FuncIntGrp>
        <ActivitiesTestInd>X</ActivitiesTestInd>
        <ActivitiesFurtherExemptPrpsInd>1</ActivitiesFurtherExemptPrpsInd>
        <ActivitiesEngagedOrgInvlmntInd>1</ActivitiesEngagedOrgInvlmntInd>
      </Form990SchAType3FuncIntGrp>
      <Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART IV, SECTION D, LINE 3:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE FOUNDATION'S BOARD INCLUDES FIVE DIRECTORS WHO HAVE BEEN APPOINTED BY JEFFERSON HOSPITAL'S BOARD. IN ADDITION, THESE JEFFERSON HOSPITAL-APPOINTED DIRECTORS SERVE AS VOTING MEMBERS ON ALL OF THE FOUNDATION'S COMMITTEES, INCLUDING THE EXECUTIVE, GOVERNANCE, GRANTS AND FINANCE COMMITTEES. AS SUCH THESE JEFFERSON HOSPITAL-APPOINTED DIRECTORS EXERCISE A SIGNIFICANT VOICE IN DETERMINING THE FOUNDATION'S INVESTMENT POLICY, GRANTMAKING GUIDELINES AND AWARDS, AND ALSO PROVIDE FINANCIAL OVERSIGHT. IN ADDITION, THE FOUNDATION ENGAGES IN CONTINUAL COMMUNICATION WITH JEFFERSON HOSPITAL MANAGEMENT, INCLUDING THE CEO OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL WHO IS REGULARLY INVITED TO THE FOUNDATION'S BOARD MEETINGS.</ExplanationTxt>
      </Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
      <Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART IV, SECTION E, LINE 2A:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE FOUNDATION SUPPORTS JEFFERSON HOSPITAL. JEFFERSON HOSPITAL'S EXEMPT PURPOSE INCLUDES IMPROVING THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF THE INDIVIDUALS IN ITS SERVICE AREA, AND THIS PURPOSE IS SUBSTANTIALLY SIMILAR TO THE FOUNDATION'S MISSION. THE FOUNDATION'S ACTIVITIES DIRECTLY FURTHER JEFFERSON HOSPITAL'S EXEMPT PURPOSE BY FOCUSING ON PROGRAMS THAT SUPPORT IMPROVING THE HEALTH AND WELL-BEING OF THE COMMUNITY OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL. THE FOUNDATION ENSURES THAT IT IS RESPONSIVE TO JEFFERSON HOSPITAL BY REMAINING IN CONTINUAL COMMUNICATION WITH JEFFERSON HOSPITAL MANAGEMENT, INCLUDING THE CEO OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL WHO IS REGULARLY INVITED TO THE FOUNDATION'S BOARD MEETING AND THROUGH PARTICIPATION IN JEFFERSON HOSPITAL'S COMMUNITY HEALTH NEEDS ASSESSMENT PROCESS. THE DETAIL OF BOTH OF THESE ITEMS IS DISCUSSED IN GREATER DETAIL IN SCHEDULE O. THE FOUNDATION ENSURES THAT ITS DIRECT FURTHERANCE ACTIVITIES CONSTITUTE SUBSTANTIALLY ALL OF ITS ACTIVITIES BECAUSE EVERY GRANT IT CONSIDERS IS REVIEWED BY A GRANTS COMMITTEE WHOSE INTERNAL GUIDELINES REQUIRE IT TO CONSIDER HOW THE GRANTS CONSIDERED ALIGN WITH BOTH THE HOSPITAL'S AND THE FOUNDATION'S MISSIONS. GRANTS THAT DO NOT MEET THIS ALIGNMENT ARE GENERALLY REJECTED.</ExplanationTxt>
      </Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
      <Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART IV, SECTION E, LINE 2B:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>PURSUANT TO SECTION 501(R) OF THE INTERNAL REVENUE CODE, JEFFERSON HOSPITAL, AS A REQUIREMENT FOR MAINTAINING ITS TAX EXEMPT STATUS, MUST DEMONSTRATE THAT IT IS ADEQUATELY ADDRESSING THE HEALTH NEEDS OF THE LOCAL COMMUNITIES IN ITS SERVICE AREA. AS PART OF THIS REQUIREMENT, JEFFERSON HOSPITAL IS REQUIRED TO ENGAGE IN A COMMUNITY HEALTH NEEDS ASSESSMENT (CHNA) AND DEVOTE RESOURCES TO PROJECTS THAT WILL AMELIORATE THE CONCERNS RAISED BY THE CHNA. BY PARTICIPATING IN THE CHNA PROCESS AND MAINTAINING CONTINUOUS COMMUNICATIONS WITH JEFFERSON HOSPITAL'S MANAGEMENT AND STAKEHOLDERS, THE FOUNDATION ENSURES THAT IT IS WELL VERSED IN THE PRIORITIES JEFFERSON HOSPITAL WISHES TO ADDRESS. THE FOUNDATION CAN THEN LEVERAGE ITS COMMUNITY CONNECTIONS TO HELP IDENTIFY AND PROMOTE ACTIVITIES THAT WILL ADVANCE THE GOALS OF JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AS DOCUMENTED IN THE CHNA, WHILE ALSO PROVIDING THE FINANCIAL RESOURCES THAT JEFFERSON HOSPITAL LACKS TO IMPLEMENT THESE PROGRAMS UNILATERALLY.</ExplanationTxt>
      </Form990ScheduleAPartVIGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleA>
    <IRS990ScheduleD documentId="RetDoc1040000001">
      <LeaseholdImprovementsGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>44257</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>13277</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>30980</BookValueAmt>
      </LeaseholdImprovementsGrp>
      <EquipmentGrp>
        <OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>61803</OtherCostOrOtherBasisAmt>
        <DepreciationAmt>35346</DepreciationAmt>
        <BookValueAmt>26457</BookValueAmt>
      </EquipmentGrp>
      <TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>57437</TotalBookValueLandBuildingsAmt>
      <FootnoteTextInd>X</FootnoteTextInd>
      <TotalRevEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>8933377</TotalRevEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>
      <NetUnrealizedGainsInvstAmt>4249648</NetUnrealizedGainsInvstAmt>
      <RevenueNotReportedAmt>4249648</RevenueNotReportedAmt>
      <RevenueSubtotalAmt>4683729</RevenueSubtotalAmt>
      <RevenueNotReportedFinclStmtAmt>0</RevenueNotReportedFinclStmtAmt>
      <TotalRevenuePerForm990Amt>4683729</TotalRevenuePerForm990Amt>
      <TotExpnsEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>4087497</TotExpnsEtcAuditedFinclStmtAmt>
      <ExpensesNotReportedAmt>0</ExpensesNotReportedAmt>
      <ExpensesSubtotalAmt>4087497</ExpensesSubtotalAmt>
      <ExpensesNotRptFinclStmtAmt>0</ExpensesNotRptFinclStmtAmt>
      <TotalExpensesPerForm990Amt>4087497</TotalExpensesPerForm990Amt>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART X, LINE 2:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE FOUNDATION ACCOUNTS FOR UNCERTAINTY IN INCOME TAXES USING A RECOGNITION THRESHOLD OF MORE-LIKELY-THAN-NOT TO BE SUSTAINED UPON EXAMINATION BY THE APPROPRIATE TAXING AUTHORITY. MEASUREMENT OF THE TAX UNCERTAINTY OCCURS IF THE RECOGNITION THRESHOLD IS MET. MANAGEMENT DETERMINED THERE WERE NO TAX UNCERTAINTIES THAT MET THE RECOGNITION THRESHOLD IN 2018 AND 2017.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleD>
    <IRS990ScheduleI documentId="RetDoc1041900001">
      <GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>1</GrantRecordsMaintainedInd>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>412 FOOD RESCUE</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>6022 BROAD STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15206</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>473476140</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>50000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>CONTINUE TO INCREASE FOOD ACCESS AND PROMOTE SUSTAINABILITY IN THE JEFFERSON AREA BY RECOVERING FOOD AND DELIVERING IT TO NONPROFIT COMMUNITY PARTNERS, PROMOTING USE OF HEALTHY FOODS BY OFFERING AN EVIDENCE-BASED FOOD EDUCATION PROGRAM, AND PILOTING THE SALE OF SNAP-ELIGIBLE, PRE-PREPARED, HEALTHY MEALS IN CORNER STORES MADE WITH RESCUED FOOD.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>ALLEGHENY COUNTY LIBRARY ASSOCIATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>22 WABASH STREET SUITE 202</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15220</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251742676</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>200000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EXPAND THE CAPACITY OF TEN SOUTH HILLS LIBRARIES TO SERVE AS STRONG COMMUNITY RESOURCES BY ASSESSING THE NEEDS OF LOCAL RESIDENTS, DEVELOPING AND IMPLEMENTING COMMUNITY PARTNERSHIPS, AND DESIGNING PROGRAMMING TO MEET UNIQUE COMMUNITY NEEDS TO SERVE NEW AND MORE PATRONS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>ALLEGHENY HEALTH NETWORKJEFFERSON HOSPITAL</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>120 FIFTH AVENUE SUITE 410</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15222</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>453674924</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>1000000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>CREATE A MODEL OF EXCELLENCE IN THE JEFFERSON HOSPITAL EMERGENCY DEPARTMENT BY BUILDING CAPACITY TO ADDRESS THE SOCIAL DETERMINANTS OF HEALTH FOR ALL PATIENTS THROUGH ENHANCED STAFF CAPACITIES, STRONGLY ESTABLISHED REFERRAL RELATIONSHIPS, IMPROVED PATIENT AND SYSTEM OUTCOMES, AND ENRICHED COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>BEVERLY'S BIRTHDAYS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>31 ROBBINS STATION ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>NORTH HUNTINGDON</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15642</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>454248006</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>20000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>CREATE POSITIVE, MEMORABLE EXPERIENCES FOR YOUNG LOW-INCOME CHILDREN AND THEIR FAMILIES AND INCREASE CAPACITY OF 16 LOCAL ORGANIZATIONS AND SIX SCHOOLS BY PROVIDING BIRTHDAY CHEER PROGRAMS TARGETED IN THE COMMUNITIES OF CLAIRTON, DUQUESNE, HOMESTEAD, AND MCKEESPORT.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>CENTER FOR HEARING AND DEAF SERVICES</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1945 FIFTH AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15219</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>250974324</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>120000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>INCREASE THE CAPACITY OF 12-15 JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE ORGANIZATIONS THAT SERVE REFUGEE, IMMIGRANT AND INTERNATIONAL POPULATIONS THROUGH A PARTNERSHIP WITH GLOBAL WORDSMITHS TO TRANSLATE DOCUMENTS, CREATE LANGUAGE ACCESS PLANS, CONDUCT TRAINING, AND SELF-FUND LANGUAGE ACCESS IN FUTURE BUDGETS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>CENTER OF LIFE</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>161 HAZELWOOD AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15207</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>010617023</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>90000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PROMOTE PROBLEM SOLVING, INDEPENDENCE, SELF-ESTEEM, AND TEAMWORK FOR JEFFERSON AREA YOUTH AND FAMILIES THROUGH A PARTNERSHIP TO INFUSE THE ARTS INTO EXISTING YOUTH AND FAMILY PROGRAMMING WHILE BUILDING CAPACITY OF JEFFERSON AREA OUT-OF-SCHOOL TIME PROVIDERS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>CRIBS FOR KIDS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>5450 SECOND AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15207</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251442806</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>45000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>IMPLEMENT COMMUNITY OUTREACH AND INTERVENTION STRATEGIES IN PARTNERSHIP WITH JEFFERSON AREA FIRST RESPONDERS, INCLUDING DISTRIBUTION OF PORTABLE CRIBS, TO DECREASE THE RISK AND REDUCE THE NUMBER OF SLEEP RELATED INFANT DEATHS AND IMPROVE RELATIONSHIPS BETWEEN JEFFERSON COMMUNITIES AND FIRST RESPONDERS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>DUQUESNE UNIVERSITY</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>600 FORBES AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15282</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251035663</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>75000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EXPLORE OPPORTUNITIES TO INCREASE CAPACITY AND ENHANCE SUSTAINABILITY FOR THE ASTHMA SCHOOL-BASED CLINIC IN CLAIRTON ELEMENTARY SCHOOL, DEVELOP A PARTNERSHIP WITH CONSUMER HEALTH COALITIONS CLAIRTON COMMUNITY HEALTH WORKERS, AND CONTINUE TO OFFER FREE ASTHMA SCREENINGS TO CLAIRTON CHILDREN AND REFER THEM TO FOLLOW-UP CARE.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>EASTERN AREA ADULT SERVICES INC</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>KEYSTONE COMMONS 607 BRADDOCK</AddressLine1Txt>
          <AddressLine2Txt>AVENUE</AddressLine2Txt>
          <CityNm>TURTLE CREEK</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15145</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251433314</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>50000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>ASSIST 100 JEFFERSON AREA OLDER ADULTS AND CAREGIVERS THROUGH INCREASING ORGANIZATIONAL CAPACITY BY ADDRESSING A SYSTEM WIDE SHORTAGE OF HOME CARE WORKERS THROUGH TRAINING AND EXPLORING NEW MODELS OF SERVICE DELIVERY FOR INCREASED EFFICIENCY AND QUALITY.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>BRENTWOOD ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>4127 BROWNSVILLE ROAD SUITE 209</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15227</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251780107</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>250000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>STRENGTHEN OPPORTUNITIES FOR JEFFERSON RESIDENTS AND ORGANIZATIONS BY INCREASING LOCAL CAPACITY FOR COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT EXPERTISE, TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE AND PROJECT MANAGEMENT WHICH ADVANCE FOUNDATION AND JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE PRIORITIES INCLUDING SUPPORT FOR PRE-DEVELOPMENT OF A COMMUNITY ENTREPRENEURIAL SPACE IN HOMESTEAD IN PARTNERSHIP WITH VOODOO BREWERY.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>BRENTWOOD ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>4127 BROWNSVILLE ROAD SUITE 209</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15227</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251780107</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>110000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EXPAND HUMAN SERVICES INFORMATION AND RESOURCES FOR CLAIRTON RESIDENTS AND ORGANIZATIONS BY STRENGTHENING THE CAPACITY OF CLAIRTON CARES TO COORDINATE AND DELIVER SERVICES AND LEVERAGE ITS KEY ROLE AS A SUBCONTRACTOR IN IMPLEMENTING THE NEIGHBORHOOD PARTNERSHIP PROGRAM.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GLASSPORT DEVELOPMENT CORPORATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>440 MONONGAHELA AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>GLASSPORT</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15045</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251570677</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>8500</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EXPAND MARKETING AND OUTREACH EFFORTS FOR THE VOLUNTEER-LED SUBSTANCE ABUSE REALITY TOUR BASED IN GLASSPORT TO PROVIDE MORE FAMILIES WITH AN EVIDENCE-BASED DRUG PREVENTION PROGRAM AND EXPAND THE TOUR TO OTHER JEFFERSON COMMUNITIES.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GLOBAL LINKS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>700 TRUMBULL DRIVE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15205</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>521629060</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>50000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PROVIDE NEEDED SURPLUS MEDICAL SUPPLIES THROUGH PARTNERSHIPS WITH THREE JEFFERSON HUMAN SERVICE AGENCIES SERVING OLDER ADULTS AND/OR LOW-INCOME INDIVIDUALS TO INCREASE ORGANIZATIONAL CAPACITY AND TO ENSURE THAT INDIVIDUALS HAVE THE NECESSARY SUPPLIES TO LEAD HEALTHY LIVES AND MAINTAIN THEIR INDEPENDENCE.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GREATER PITTSBURGH COMMUNITY FOOD BANK</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1 N LINDEN STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>DUQUESNE</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15110</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251420599</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>68000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PILOT THE DISTRIBUTION OF MEDICALLY TAILORED FOOD BOXES TO FOOD INSECURE PATIENTS AT JEFFERSON HOSPITAL AND SQUIRREL HILL HEALTH CENTER AS AN EFFECTIVE TOOL FROM THE PATIENT, COMMUNITY, AND CLINICAL PERSPECTIVE IN RECOVERY AND/OR IMPROVED HEALTH STABILITY.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GREATER PITTSBURGH COMMUNITY FOOD BANK</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1 N LINDEN STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>DUQUESNE</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15110</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251420599</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>10000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PILOT A BACKPACK FOOD DISTRIBUTION PROGRAM IN PARTNERSHIP WITH ELIZABETH FORWARD SCHOOL DISTRICT HIGH SCHOOL TO SERVE 25 STUDENTS WEEKLY TO ADDRESS A GROWING NEED AMONG LOCAL FAMILIES.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GREATER PITTSBURGH LITERACY COUNCIL</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>411 SEVENTH AVENUE SUITE 550</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15219</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251392652</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>60000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>MEET THE INCREASED DEMAND FOR ESSENTIAL LITERACY TRAINING FOR OVER 60 LOCAL ADULTS AND FAMILIES BY ADDING AN ONSITE JEFFERSON AREA COORDINATOR, ADDITIONAL VOLUNTEERS, CLASSES AND NEW AGENCY PARTNERSHIPS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GWEN'S GIRLS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>711 WEST COMMONS THIRD FLOOR</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15212</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>753114136</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>35000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>CONTINUE TO STRENGTHEN PROGRAM OPTIONS AND QUALITY TO CLAIRTON YOUTH AND FAMILIES THROUGH A STRATEGIC PLANNING PROCESS TO FINALIZE A PARENT-SUBSIDIARY AFFILIATION BETWEEN GWENS GIRLS AND YOUTH OPPORTUNITIES DEVELOPMENT, INTEGRATE OPERATIONS, AND DEVELOP AN ACTION PLAN.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>GWEN'S GIRLS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>711 WEST COMMONS THIRD FLOOR</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15212</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>753114136</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>2000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>SUPPORT INCREASED ENGAGEMENT IN THE BIMONTHLY TOPICAL MEETINGS OF THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVES EAT N EDUCATE ACTION TEAM.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>IN OUR BACKYARDS INC (IOBY)</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>540 PRESIDENT STREET 1ST FLOOR</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>BROOKLYN</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>NY</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>11215</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>263283639</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>60000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>BUILD THE CAPACITY OF SMALL, VOLUNTEER-LED, JEFFERSON ORGANIZATIONS TO MORE EFFECTIVELY SERVE LOCAL COMMUNITIES THROUGH ONE-ON-ONE COACHING, TRAINING IN ONLINE CROWDFUNDING, AND CREATION OF A DOLLAR-FOR- DOLLAR MATCH FUND FOR PROJECTS THAT MAKES JEFFERSON COMMUNITIES HEALTHIER AND MORE LIVABLE.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>BOYS &amp; GIRLS CLUBS OF WESTERN PA</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>5432 BUTLER STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15201</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251206970</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>50000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>ENGAGE 225 TEENS AND PRE-TEENS AGES 12-18 FROM DUQUESNE, MCKEESPORT, AND THE SURROUNDING MON VALLEY AREAS TO CONTINUE TO PARTICIPATE IN A TEENCLUB PROGRAM AND ENHANCE THE PROGRAM TO PROMOTE CAREER READINESS, SOCIAL DEVELOPMENT, AND LEADERSHIP SKILLS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>METHODIST UNION OF SOCIAL AGENCIES (MUSA)</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>PO BOX 433</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>HOMESTEAD</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15120</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251368765</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>SUPPORT STRATEGIES TO INCREASE FULL YEAR ENGAGEMENT AND ENHANCE QUALITY IN AFFORDABLE, OUT-OF-SCHOOL TIME PROGRAMMING FOR 130 LOW-INCOME YOUTH AND FAMILIES FROM HOMESTEAD, WEST HOMESTEAD, MUNHALL, AND SURROUNDING COMMUNITIES.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>NEIGHBORWORKS WESTERN PENNSYLVANIA</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>710 5TH AVENUE SUITE 1000</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15219</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251195085</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>30000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PROMOTE FINANCIAL WELLNESS AND REDUCE THE FINANCIAL STRESSORS THAT NEGATIVELY IMPACT HEALTH AND WELLNESS FOR 120 SOUTH HILLS RESIDENTS BY OFFERING FINANCIAL EDUCATION WORKSHOPS AND ONE-ON-ONE COUNSELING AND COACHING.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>PENN STATE GREATER ALLEGHENY</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>4000 UNIVERSITY DRIVE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>MCKEESPORT</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15132</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PROMOTE A PARTNERSHIP OF PENN STATE GREATER ALLEGHENY AND THE CITY OF MCKEESPORT TO BUILD AND LEVERAGE THE OUTREACH CAPACITY OF THE PENN STATE-MCKEESPORT COMMUNITY CENTER TO ADDRESS JOBLESSNESS AND FOOD INSECURITY IN MCKEESPORT AND OTHER MON VALLEY COMMUNITIES.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>PLEASANT HILLS POLICE DEPARTMENT</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>410 E BRUCETON ROAD</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15236</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <CashGrantAmt>41000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>INCREASE THE OPPORTUNITY TO SAVE JEFFERSON RESIDENTS LIVES FROM SUDDEN CARDIAC ARREST THROUGH THE PURCHASE OF 30 AUTOMATED EXTERNAL DEFIBRILLATORS (AED) TO BE INSTALLED IN POLICE PATROL VEHICLES SERVING BALDWIN BOROUGH, PLEASANT HILLS BOROUGH, AND WEST MIFFLIN BOROUGH.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>SALTWORKS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>569 N NEVILLE STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15213</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251395314</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>10000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>CONTINUE TO INCREASE KNOWLEDGE ABOUT THE OPIOID EPIDEMIC AS A PREVENTION TOOL FOR HUNDREDS OF JEFFERSON AREA MIDDLE AND HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS AND TEACHERS THROUGH LIVE THEATER PRODUCTIONS, CURRICULUM GUIDES FOR TEACHERS, AND A QUESTION AND ANSWER SESSION WITH YOUNG ACTORS WHO HAVE RECEIVED TRAINING ON ADDICTION ISSUES.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>SISTERS PLACE INC</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>418 MITCHELL AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>CLAIRTON</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15025</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251728330</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>125000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>ASSIST HOMELESS SINGLE PARENT FAMILIES THROUGH HOLISTIC SUPPORTIVE SERVICES INCLUDING TRANSPORTATION, OUT OF SCHOOL PROGRAMS, AND BASIC RESOURCES AND BUILD ORGANIZATIONAL CAPACITY THROUGH A STRATEGIC PLANNING PROCESS TO PROACTIVELY POSITION SISTERS PLACE FOR CONTINUED SUCCESS IN THE FUTURE.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>STEEL RIVERS COUNCIL OF GOVERNMENTS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1705 MAPLE ST</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>HOMESTEAD</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15120</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251245642</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>DEFINE A VISION AND BUILD CONSENSUS AROUND PRIMARY GOALS AND OBJECTIVES FOR HEALTH ACCESS IN THE MON VALLEY THROUGH DATA ANALYSIS, COMMUNITY SURVEYS AND ENGAGEMENT, GIS MAPPING TO UNDERSTAND THE OVERLAY OF HEALTH SERVICES, AND CREATION OF A REPORT TO DISTRIBUTE TO KEY STAKEHOLDERS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>STUDENT CONSERVATION ASSOCIATION</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>4245 NORTH FAIRFAX DRIVE SUITE 825</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>ARLINGTON</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>VA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>22203</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>910880684</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EMPLOY 20 JEFFERSON AREA YOUTH, IN PARTNERSHIP WITH LOCAL ORGANIZATION MELTING POT MINISTRIES, FOR SOUTH PARK CONSERVATION WORK WHILE INCREASING PHYSICAL ACTIVITY, KNOWLEDGE OF ENVIRONMENTAL AND HEALTHY LIFESTYLE HABITS, ACCESS TO TRAINED MENTORS, AND IMPORTANT EMPLOYMENT SKILLS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>THE FORBES FUNDS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>FIVE PPG PLACE SUITE 250</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15222</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251418095</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>BUILD THE LEADERSHIP CAPACITY OF LOCAL ORGANIZATIONS TO MORE EFFECTIVELY SERVE THE COMMUNITY THROUGH INDIVIDUAL COACHING AND TRAINING AND THE ADDITION OF PEER LEARNING COHORTS OFFERED BY HIGHLY EXPERIENCED RETIRED EXECUTIVES AND GROUP TRAININGS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>THE MISSION CONTINUES</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1141 SOUTH 7TH STREET</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>ST LOUIS</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>MO</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>63104</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>208742553</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>100000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>POST 9/11 VETERANS AND JEFFERSON COMMUNITY MEMBERS WILL BENEFIT BY VOLUNTEERING WITH THE JEFFERSON SERVICE PLATOON SUPPORTING THE LOCAL REFUGEE AND IMMIGRANT POPULATION THROUGH PARTNERSHIPS WITH COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>UNITED WAY OF SOUTHWESTERN PENNSYLVANIA</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>1250 PENN AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15222</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251043578</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>70000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>EXPAND VOLUNTEERISM THAT CONNECTS GENERATIONS AND STRENGTHENS VITAL TIES OF SUPPORT IN JEFFERSON COMMUNITIES THROUGH INCREASING SUPPORT FOR OLDER ADULTS AND CAREGIVERS AND PROVIDING MENTORS TO MIDDLE SCHOOL YOUTH.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>VENTURE OUTDOORS</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>33 TERMINAL WAY SUITE 537A</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15219</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>203275291</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>40000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>ENGAGE YOUTH IN THE HEALTHY BENEFITS OF ACTIVE OUTDOOR ACTIVITY AND EXPAND PARTICIPATION TO FAMILIES AND OLDER ADULTS THROUGH TARGETED OUTDOOR PROGRAMMING PROMOTING HEALTH AND WELLNESS.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <RecipientTable>
        <RecipientBusinessName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>WQED</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </RecipientBusinessName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>4802 FIFTH AVENUE</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>15213</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <RecipientEIN>251010296</RecipientEIN>
        <IRCSectionDesc>501(C)(3)</IRCSectionDesc>
        <CashGrantAmt>50000</CashGrantAmt>
        <PurposeOfGrantTxt>PROMOTE FAMILY ENGAGEMENT AND POSITIVE CONNECTIONS TO LEARNING THROUGH EXPANSION OF WQEDS READY TO LEARN PROJECT FOR YOUNG SOUTH HILLS FAMILIES, THROUGH TWELVE, FOUR-WEEK HIGH-QUALITY FAMILY CREATIVE LEARNING WORKSHOPS OFFERED IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE AT THREE COMMUNITY SITES INCLUDING BALDWIN BOROUGH PUBLIC LIBRARY AND WHITEHALL PUBLIC LIBRARY.</PurposeOfGrantTxt>
      </RecipientTable>
      <Total501c3OrgCnt>33</Total501c3OrgCnt>
      <TotalOtherOrgCnt>0</TotalOtherOrgCnt>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>PART I, LINE 2:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>MONITORING OF GRANTS BEGINS WITH THE GRANT PROPOSAL PROCESS. APPLICANT ORGANIZATIONS ARE ASKED TO INDICATE GOALS AND MEASURABLE OBJECTIVES WHICH WILL BE ACCOMPLISHED IF THEIR PROGRAM OR PROJECT IS FUNDED. THEY ARE ALSO ASKED TO PROVIDE A NUMBER OF KEY DOCUMENTS WITH THE PROPOSAL, INCLUDING: BOARD LIST, ORGANIZATION BUDGET, MOST RECENT AUDIT, 990 TAX RETURN, STRATEGIC PLAN AND LETTERS OF SUPPORT. TAX-EXEMPT STATUS IS ALSO CHECKED. WHEN A GRANT IS AWARDED, AN ORGANIZATION IS ASKED TO SIGN A LETTER OF AGREEMENT BEFORE THE CHECK AWARD IS ISSUED. THE LETTER LISTS A NUMBER OF TERMS AND CONDITIONS, INCLUDING THE NEED TO PROVIDE PROGRESS REPORTS AT SPECIFIC DATES, PRIOR WRITTEN APPROVAL OF ANY SUBSTANTIAL VARIANCES FROM BUDGET OR INTENT, RECORD-KEEPING, AND REQUIRED NOTIFICATIONS. MOST GRANTS REQUIRE A MID-YEAR PROGRESS REPORT AND A YEAR-END PROGRESS REPORT WHICH INDICATE RESULTS ON OBJECTIVES, INFORMATION ABOUT INTENDED AND UNINTENDED RESULTS, CHALLENGES AND A LINE ITEM FINANCIAL REPORT. STAFF REVIEW THE REPORTS AND CONFER WITH THE APPLICANT IF NEEDED. MULTI-YEAR GRANTS REQUIRE REVIEW OF A REPORT FOR EACH GRANT PERIOD BEFORE BOARD RELEASE OF FUNDING FOR THE NEXT PERIOD. SUMMARIES OF THESE REPORTS ARE PROVIDED TO THE GRANT COMMITTEE FOR DISCUSSION OF THE RESULTS AND ANY RECOMMENDED ACTION. THE COMMITTEE SHARES THE RESULTS AND RECOMMENDATIONS WITH THE BOARD FOR ANY ACTION. IN ADDITION, STAFF BUILD ONGOING RELATIONSHIPS AND MONITOR THROUGHOUT THE GRANT PERIOD THROUGH SITE VISITS, GROUP GRANTEE ORIENTATION SESSIONS AND TECHNICAL ASSISTANCE.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleI>
    <IRS990ScheduleJ documentId="RetDoc1042400001">
      <CompensationCommitteeInd>X</CompensationCommitteeInd>
      <CompensationSurveyInd>X</CompensationSurveyInd>
      <BoardOrCommitteeApprovalInd>X</BoardOrCommitteeApprovalInd>
      <SeverancePaymentInd>0</SeverancePaymentInd>
      <SupplementalNonqualRtrPlanInd>0</SupplementalNonqualRtrPlanInd>
      <EquityBasedCompArrngmInd>0</EquityBasedCompArrngmInd>
      <CompBasedOnRevenueOfFlngOrgInd>0</CompBasedOnRevenueOfFlngOrgInd>
      <CompBsdOnRevRelatedOrgsInd>0</CompBsdOnRevRelatedOrgsInd>
      <CompBsdNetEarnsFlngOrgInd>0</CompBsdNetEarnsFlngOrgInd>
      <CompBsdNetEarnsRltdOrgsInd>0</CompBsdNetEarnsRltdOrgsInd>
      <AnyNonFixedPaymentsInd>0</AnyNonFixedPaymentsInd>
      <InitialContractExceptionInd>0</InitialContractExceptionInd>
      <RltdOrgOfficerTrstKeyEmplGrp>
        <PersonNm>MARY PHAN-GRUBER</PersonNm>
        <TitleTxt>EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR/ASST TR</TitleTxt>
        <BaseCompensationFilingOrgAmt>147000</BaseCompensationFilingOrgAmt>
        <CompensationBasedOnRltdOrgsAmt>0</CompensationBasedOnRltdOrgsAmt>
        <BonusFilingOrganizationAmount>0</BonusFilingOrganizationAmount>
        <BonusRelatedOrganizationsAmt>0</BonusRelatedOrganizationsAmt>
        <OtherCompensationFilingOrgAmt>0</OtherCompensationFilingOrgAmt>
        <OtherCompensationRltdOrgsAmt>0</OtherCompensationRltdOrgsAmt>
        <DeferredCompensationFlngOrgAmt>5880</DeferredCompensationFlngOrgAmt>
        <DeferredCompRltdOrgsAmt>0</DeferredCompRltdOrgsAmt>
        <NontaxableBenefitsFilingOrgAmt>16382</NontaxableBenefitsFilingOrgAmt>
        <NontaxableBenefitsRltdOrgsAmt>0</NontaxableBenefitsRltdOrgsAmt>
        <TotalCompensationFilingOrgAmt>169262</TotalCompensationFilingOrgAmt>
        <TotalCompensationRltdOrgsAmt>0</TotalCompensationRltdOrgsAmt>
        <CompReportPrior990FilingOrgAmt>0</CompReportPrior990FilingOrgAmt>
        <CompReportPrior990RltdOrgsAmt>0</CompReportPrior990RltdOrgsAmt>
      </RltdOrgOfficerTrstKeyEmplGrp>
    </IRS990ScheduleJ>
    <IRS990ScheduleO documentId="RetDoc1044400001">
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART III, LINE 4D, OTHER PROGRAM SERVICES, CONTINUED:</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE SINCE 2015, THE FOUNDATION HAS HOSTED AN EVOLVING NETWORK WHICH HAS GROWN TO OVER 80-MEMBER ORGANIZATIONS AND THE ADDITION OF A STAFF MEMBER FOR SUPPORT. ORGANIZATIONS INCLUDE HUMAN SERVICES, LIBRARIES, CHURCHES, COMMUNITY DEVELOPMENT, LOCAL UNIVERSITIES, AND EVEN OTHER FUNDERS SUCH AS UNITED WAY. THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE IS COMMITTED TO BRINGING TOGETHER CHANGE-MAKERS TO POSITIVELY IMPACT THE HEALTH AND VITALITY OF COMMUNITIES SOUTH OF PITTSBURGH. THE COLLABORATIVE'S VISION INCLUDES SERVING AS AN INCUBATOR FOR IDEAS AND PROMISING PRACTICES, IMPROVING THE CAPACITY OF COMMUNITY-SERVING ORGANIZATIONS AND FACILITATING GROUP ACTION ON COMMUNITY ASPIRATIONS. ITS CURRENT PRIORITIES INCLUDE: BEHAVIORAL HEALTH, FAMILY AND RESIDENT ENGAGEMENT AND WORKFORCE DEVELOPMENT. THE FULL COLLABORATIVE HOSTS MEMBER MEETINGS FIVE TIMES A YEAR, AVERAGING 75 PARTICIPANTS WITH EXTENSIVE NETWORKING, INTERACTIVE PRESENTATIONS ON A FOCUS ISSUE OR SKILL, REPORTS ON ITS ACTION TEAMS, NETWORKING AND SHARING AMONG ORGANIZATIONS. A VISION COUNCIL PROVIDES GUIDANCE TO THE COLLABORATIVE AND INCLUDES OVER A DOZEN LEADERS OF COMMUNITY ORGANIZATIONS. COLLABORATIVE ACTIVITIES ALSO INCLUDE A PEER-LED EDUCATION SERIES, A COMMUNITY ENGAGEMENT TEAM, CERTIFIED MENTAL HEALTH FIRST AID TRAINERS, AND OTHER ISSUE-BASED ACTION TEAMS. ANOTHER OUTGROWTH OF THE JEFFERSON COMMUNITY COLLABORATIVE IS THE HIGHLY-REGARDED JEFFERSON COMMUNITY DIRECTORY: A RESOURCE GUIDE FOR CONNECTIONS WHICH THE COLLABORATIVE DEVELOPED IN PARTNERSHIP WITH THE FOUNDATION AND JEFFERSON HOSPITAL/ALLEGHENY HEALTH NETWORK. THE FOUNDATION PUBLISHED THE THIRD EDITION OF THE DIRECTORY IN THE SPRING OF 2018 WHICH INCLUDED 60 NEW PROGRAMS AND 2 NEW RESOURCE CATEGORIES (IMMIGRANTS AND WORKFORCE). THE 141-PAGE INDEXED COMMUNITY DIRECTORY CONTINUES TO BE DISTRIBUTED TO KEY STAKEHOLDERSINCLUDING NONPROFIT PROVIDERS, LIBRARIES, CHURCHES, HEALTHCARE PROFESSIONALS, AND FIRST RESPONDERS AND IT IS ALSO AVAILABLE ONLINE. IN ADDITION TO THE COLLABORATIVE NOTED ABOVE, THE FOUNDATION ALSO CONVENES OTHER GROUPS TO PROMOTE COOPERATION FOR LARGER COMMUNITY BENEFIT AND INCREASED QUALITY AND CAPACITY. IN PARTNERSHIP WITH JEFFERSON HOSPITAL, THE FOUNDATION HOSTED A CLERGY CONVENING FOCUSED ON RESOURCES FOR OLDER ADULTS. THE FOUNDATION REGULARLY HOSTS MEETINGS OF LOCAL OUT OF SCHOOL TIME PROVIDERSWHO SERVE YOUTH WITH AFTERSCHOOL AND SUMMER PROGRAMMING. THE FOUNDATION ALSO HOSTED A GATHERING OF KEY STAKEHOLDERS FOCUSED ON THE OPIOID OVERDOSE EPIDEMIC IN OUR LOCAL AREA.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION A, LINE 2</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>BOARD MEMBER GARY EVANS IS THE SPOUSE OF BOARD MEMBER KAREN EVANS. DURING THE TAX YEAR, BOARD MEMBER HARRY SICHI WAS A PARTNER IN THE SAME FIRM FOR WHICH BOARD MEMBER EDWARD MARASCO WORKED.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 11B</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE FINAL VERSION OF THE 990 IS PROVIDED TO BOARD MEMBERS FOR REVIEW. INFORMATION AND ITEMS CAN BE CLARIFIED AND CONFIRMED WITH EXECUTIVE MANAGEMENT AND OTHER MEMBERS OF THE BOARD. CORRECTIONS AND CLARIFICATIONS ARE SUBMITTED OR SUGGESTED PRIOR TO THE FILING OF THE RETURN.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 12C</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>PERIODIC REVIEWS ARE CONDUCTED AND MAY INCLUDE ASSISTANCE FROM OUTSIDE ADVISORS TO ENSURE JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION IS OPERATING IN A MANNER CONSISTENT WITH ITS CHARITABLE PURPOSE AND DOES NOT ENGAGE IN ACTIVITIES THAT COULD JEOPARDIZE ITS TAX EXEMPT STATUS. A DISCLOSURE PROCEDURE OUTLINED IN THE CONFLICT OF INTEREST POLICY INCLUDES SUBMISSION OF THE ANNUAL DISCLOSURE STATEMENT AS WELL AS LETTERS, MEMOS, OR OTHER DISCLOSURES TO THE BOARD. THIS PROCEDURE IS MONITORED BY OTHER MEMBERS OF THE BOARD AS WELL AS LEGAL COUNSEL. THE SCOPE OF COVERAGE FOR THE CONFLICT OF INTEREST POLICY IS DIRECTED TOWARDS "POTENTIALLY INTERESTED PARTIES" INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO: DIRECTORS, OFFICERS, KEY EMPLOYEES, MEMBERS OF A COMMITTEE WITH BOARD DELEGATED POWERS, PERSONS WHO HAVE AUTHORITY TO ENTER INTO CONTRACTS OR AGREEMENTS, PERSONS WITH ACCESS TO RESTRICTED, SENSITIVE, OR CONFIDENTIAL INFORMATION WHICH COULD BE VALUABLE TO NON-JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION ENTITIES, AND PERSONS WITH A SIGNIFICANT FINANCIAL INTEREST OR INFLUENTIAL INTEREST. JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION PRESIDENT AND CHIEF OPERATING OFFICER, BY AUTHORITY OF THE BOARD, ARE THE DESIGNATED ADMINISTRATORS FOR INTERPRETATION AND IMPLEMENTATION OF THIS POLICY AND ALL PROCEDURES RELATING TO IT. FAILURE TO COMPLY WITH THIS POLICY MAY INCLUDE A DETERMINATION FOR THE POTENTIALLY INTERESTED PARTY TO SEVER ALL TIES WITH JEFFERSON REGIONAL FOUNDATION. THE GOVERNANCE COMMITTEE IS IN PLACE AND IN ITS COMMITTEE CHARTER HAS ADDITIONAL OVERSIGHT TO DEVELOP AND UPDATE CONFLICT OF INTEREST AND ETHICAL GUIDELINES FOR THE BOARD, PROVIDE BOARD EDUCATION ON THESE MATTERS, AND MAKE RECOMMENDATIONS REGARDING UPDATES OR IMPLEMENTATION.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION B, LINE 15</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE OF THE BOARD PROVIDES OVERSIGHT OF THE COMPENSATION PROCESS AS IT IS DESIGNATED TO SERVE AS PERSONNEL COMMITTEE. THE COMMITTEE IS LED IN PERSONNEL FUNCTIONS BY THE PRESIDENT AND CEO OF THE FOUNDATION. AS PART OF ITS ENGAGEMENT WITH THE FOUNDATION, AN OUTSIDE CONSULTING FIRM WHICH SPECIALIZES IN NONPROFIT TALENT MANAGEMENT PROVIDED COMPARABLE COMPENSATION INFORMATION FOR THE FOUNDATION'S KEY COMPENSATED POSITIONS, INCLUDING THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR AND PROGRAM OFFICER. TWO PRIMARY SOURCES WERE USED TO DEVELOP BENCHMARK INFORMATION: A GRANTMAKERS SALARY AND BENEFIT SURVEY COMPILED BY THE COUNCIL ON FOUNDATIONS AND A REGIONAL NONPROFIT SURVEY PUBLISHED BY THE UNITED WAY IN COLLABORATION WITH A LOCAL UNIVERSITY'S NONPROFIT MANAGEMENT PROGRAM. THIS INFORMATION PROVIDED DETAIL ON SALARY RANGES RELATIVE TO THE ASSET SIZE OF SIMILAR ORGANIZATIONS. THE EXECUTIVE COMMITTEE REVIEWED ALL OF THIS INFORMATION IN DETERMINING COMPENSATION, MADE ITS DETERMINATIONS, AND FULLY REPORTED ITS DELIBERATIONS AND ACTIONS DIRECTLY TO THE BOARD. THE REVIEW AND APPROVAL PROCESS FOR THE DETERMINATION OF COMPENSATION IS DOCUMENTED VIA BOARD AND COMMITTEE MINUTES.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
      <SupplementalInformationDetail>
        <FormAndLineReferenceDesc>FORM 990, PART VI, SECTION C, LINE 19</FormAndLineReferenceDesc>
        <ExplanationTxt>THE FORM 990 IS POSTED ON THE FOUNDATION'S WEBSITE. THE FOUNDATION ALSO PRODUCES AN ANNUAL REPORT OF GRANT AWARD INFORMATION WHICH IS DISTRIBUTED IN PRINT FORM AND IS AVAILABLE ON THE FOUNDATION'S WEBSITE. THE CONFLICT OF INTEREST POLICY CAN BE MADE AVAILABLE TO THE PUBLIC UPON REQUEST.</ExplanationTxt>
      </SupplementalInformationDetail>
    </IRS990ScheduleO>
    <IRS990ScheduleR documentId="RetDoc1043400001">
      <IdRelatedTaxExemptOrgGrp>
        <DisregardedEntityName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>JEFFERSON HOSPITAL</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </DisregardedEntityName>
        <USAddress>
          <AddressLine1Txt>P O BOX 18119 COAL VALLEY RD</AddressLine1Txt>
          <CityNm>PITTSBURGH</CityNm>
          <StateAbbreviationCd>PA</StateAbbreviationCd>
          <ZIPCd>152360119</ZIPCd>
        </USAddress>
        <EIN>251260215</EIN>
        <PrimaryActivitiesTxt>HOSPITAL</PrimaryActivitiesTxt>
        <LegalDomicileStateCd>PA</LegalDomicileStateCd>
        <ExemptCodeSectionTxt>501(C)(3)</ExemptCodeSectionTxt>
        <PublicCharityStatusTxt>LINE 3</PublicCharityStatusTxt>
        <DirectControllingEntityName>
          <BusinessNameLine1Txt>ALLEGHENY HEALTH NETWORK</BusinessNameLine1Txt>
        </DirectControllingEntityName>
        <ControlledOrganizationInd>0</ControlledOrganizationInd>
      </IdRelatedTaxExemptOrgGrp>
      <ReceiptOfIntAnntsRntsRyltsInd>0</ReceiptOfIntAnntsRntsRyltsInd>
      <GiftGrntOrCapContriToOthOrgInd>1</GiftGrntOrCapContriToOthOrgInd>
      <GiftGrntCapContriFromOthOrgInd>0</GiftGrntCapContriFromOthOrgInd>
      <LoansOrGuaranteesToOtherOrgInd>0</LoansOrGuaranteesToOtherOrgInd>
      <LoansOrGuaranteesFromOthOrgInd>0</LoansOrGuaranteesFromOthOrgInd>
      <DivRelatedOrganizationInd>0</DivRelatedOrganizationInd>
      <AssetSaleToOtherOrgInd>0</AssetSaleToOtherOrgInd>
      <AssetPurchaseFromOtherOrgInd>0</AssetPurchaseFromOtherOrgInd>
      <AssetExchangeInd>0</AssetExchangeInd>
      <RentalOfFacilitiesToOthOrgInd>0</RentalOfFacilitiesToOthOrgInd>
      <RentalOfFcltsFromOthOrgInd>1</RentalOfFcltsFromOthOrgInd>
      <PerformOfServicesForOthOrgInd>1</PerformOfServicesForOthOrgInd>
      <PerformOfServicesByOtherOrgInd>0</PerformOfServicesByOtherOrgInd>
      <SharingOfFacilitiesInd>1</SharingOfFacilitiesInd>
      <PaidEmployeesSharingInd>0</PaidEmployeesSharingInd>
      <ReimbursementPaidToOtherOrgInd>1</ReimbursementPaidToOtherOrgInd>
      <ReimbursementPaidByOtherOrgInd>0</ReimbursementPaidByOtherOrgInd>
      <TransferToOtherOrgInd>0</TransferToOtherOrgInd>
      <TransferFromOtherOrgInd>0</TransferFromOtherOrgInd>
    </IRS990ScheduleR>
  </ReturnData>
</Return>